<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-22T03:46:22+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Hiatus</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Hiatus" /><published>2022-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Moving-boxes.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/moving-boxes.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Moving boxes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My family and I are moving! It’s only a short distance, but it still means I need to take down all
of the permanently installed shack components like my QTH antennas. I’ll have to rely on my mobile
and portable gear for a while. It also means I won’t have much spare time for ham projects until
everything is moved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, Dave Casler just posted a video about a practice that luckily I’ve already
been following: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2TvdvcE2cJQ&quot;&gt;Keep the boxes!&lt;/a&gt; That should make the
move (at least for the shack) a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish us luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Motorola DMR Radios for Hams</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motorola DMR Radios for Hams" /><published>2022-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that came out of my trip to Westcreek was a renewed interest in getting Motorola
radios to work for myself. I originally became interested in this back in February when RMHAM
University did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aUFTMX7Ys00&quot;&gt;class&lt;/a&gt; on using commercial DMR radios
from Motorola and Kenwood for ham radio purposes. Among other things, the Motorola section of the
class covered the very important difference between using the old and new versions of the customer
programming software (CPS). The class piqued my interest and I picked up a sleek Motorola SL-300 but
didn’t actually get very far programming it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-10-02-moto-sl300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Motorola SL-300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So over the past couple of weeks, I’ve tried to keep track of everything I needed to do to get
licenses for and successfully program one of these Motorola radios. Ultimately I needed to get the
TRBO CPS license as well as a wideband (25khz) entitlement from Motorola. There seems to be a lot of
outdated information out there, so hopefully this will be updated advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, note that the Motorola radio website is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.motorolasolutions.com&quot;&gt;https://www.motorolasolutions.com&lt;/a&gt;; just plain motorola.com is
for the cell phone division. I got an account on motorolasolutions.com, but that only gave me access
to the consumer side with FRS/GMRS/MURS radios. To order the necessary part numbers, I had to
contact customer service and have them upgrade my account to a business account with a 10-digit
customer ID. It sounds like this is a common arrangement for hams. Once they did that, I was able to
access &lt;a href=&quot;https://myview.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;https://myview.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I went on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://learning.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;http://learning.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt; and took training
course &lt;em&gt;PRD0001: FCC Narrowbanding Mandate Training&lt;/em&gt; which carefully explained that wideband FM
channels are no longer allowed on commercial bands, only on ham radio bands. That only took about 15
minutes to complete. After I finished that, I had to again contact customer service and have them
manually verify completion and open up the option to order the 25khz entitlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all of that was done I was able to go back to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;https://shop.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt; and order part numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HKVN4362A for the TRBO CPS, which became free in February of 2022&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HKVN4046A for the 25khz entitlement, also free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-09-10-motorola-cart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Motorola Solutions shopping cart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all of this hassle, I was finally able to download the TRBO CPS 2 from MyView, add the
wideband entitlement and program to my heart’s content. I wouldn’t really say I’m happy with CPS 2
because there is no import/export functionality, but considering there’s no other option with
Motorola radios, I guess I’ll just be happy it works at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line here is that when working with Motorola equipment as a ham, don’t expect to be able
to do anything self-service. Contact customer support; it’s relatively quick and painless, and you
won’t get far any other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of the things that came out of my trip to Westcreek was a renewed interest in getting Motorola radios to work for myself. I originally became interested in this back in February when RMHAM University did a class on using commercial DMR radios from Motorola and Kenwood for ham radio purposes. Among other things, the Motorola section of the class covered the very important difference between using the old and new versions of the customer programming software (CPS). The class piqued my interest and I picked up a sleek Motorola SL-300 but didn’t actually get very far programming it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Westcreek</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/08/06/westcreek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Westcreek" /><published>2022-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/08/06/westcreek</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/08/06/westcreek.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I had the opportunity to help RMHAM with a site expansion. The club was recently awarded a
grant from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://grants.ardc.net/&quot;&gt;ARDC&lt;/a&gt; to expand the RMHAM IP microwave network and linked
DMR system. There were two teams to set up two differnt sides of a new link: Limon and Westcreek. I
joined the Westcreek crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-08-06-building.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Westcreek building&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-08-06-tower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Westcreek tower&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some of the more experienced folks climbed the tower to mount the new antennas and microwave
radios, I was able to help set up the data center equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-08-06-inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Westcreek data center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked hard starting in the morning. By the afternoon we started to get typical Front Range
monsoon thunderstorms which forced the crew off the tower, and we weren’t able to get the two dishes
peaked with each other. But all of the equipment is mounted and connected in the data center, so it
should be a simple matter to get them peaked on another day. This was a great learning experience!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I had the opportunity to help RMHAM with a site expansion. The club was recently awarded a grant from the ARDC to expand the RMHAM IP microwave network and linked DMR system. There were two teams to set up two differnt sides of a new link: Limon and Westcreek. I joined the Westcreek crew.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Field Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/26/field-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field Day" /><published>2022-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/26/field-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/26/field-day.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, my daughter Kaylee and I drove up to Park County, Colorado to take part in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://rmham.org/&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain Ham Radio&lt;/a&gt;’s expedition for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrl.org/field-day&quot;&gt;ARRL Field Day&lt;/a&gt;! Despite hanging out with RMHAM for a few years now,
this is the first time I’ve made the pilgrimage. The site is an empty mountain residential lot about
2 hours from metro Denver where I live, so it’s a bit of a trek. However, it was definitely worth
it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-25-site.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Field Day site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaylee and I were greeted by a small city of about 10 RVs plus several comm vans and trailers. All
told, about 30 folks were running 3 “official” transmitters plus a few accessory ones, running
voice, CW and FT8 over many bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-25-ft8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wayne N0POH and Kaylee running FT8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaylee isn’t licensed yet, but she got to try out a few HF contacts at the Get-On-The-Air station!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-25-gota.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lisa K0LMH and Kaylee at GOTA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the awesomeness happening, I think Kaylee’s favorite part of the trip was dinner! I got
to have some eyeball QSOs (contacts) with some of my favorite folks in the community, and the food
was fantastic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-25-dinner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Field Day Dinner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaylee and I only stayed for a few hours, but I think I have a partner in crime to convince the rest
of the family to come make a camping/RV trip next year! I’ll have to start working with Kaylee on
getting her own callsign, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday, my daughter Kaylee and I drove up to Park County, Colorado to take part in Rocky Mountain Ham Radio’s expedition for ARRL Field Day! Despite hanging out with RMHAM for a few years now, this is the first time I’ve made the pilgrimage. The site is an empty mountain residential lot about 2 hours from metro Denver where I live, so it’s a bit of a trek. However, it was definitely worth it!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30" /><published>2022-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-02-CLR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;City Lights Ridge site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dirty30.org/&quot;&gt;Golden Gate Dirty 30&lt;/a&gt; ultramarathon. It’s always an annual
highlight for Colorado amateur radio emergency organizations because it takes many of our teams
coming together to support this complex event. Hundreds of crazy runners (this year it was
about 300) attempt the 30 mile/50 kilometer course through 7,000 feet/2,100 meters of elevation
climb and descent in a mountainous park with very little cell phone coverage. The ham team’s job is
to make sure every one of them comes down off the mountain before it gets dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain Ham&lt;/a&gt; tech team was on-site early setting up
our IP-over-microwave network. We use the network to connect the 4 aid stations and one mountaintop
checkpoint to the command center at the start/finish line. Each of these sites has RFID readers that
can read the runners’ bibs and check them in as they run past. We also need one more site that the
runners never see: a central point that can see most of the others by line-of-sight which gets set
up on City Lights Ridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second year that City Lights Ridge was my responsibility. About six of us hiked
equipment up to the site and got it all set up and aligned with the other sites. After that, it was
my job to monitor the network and make sure everything stayed running through the race Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-02-k0swe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For monitoring the network, I made use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://prinmath.com/ham/cping.zip&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cping&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; written by
one of my mentors, Willem &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AC0KQ&lt;/code&gt;. It’s a command-line utility that will simply ping a number of
configured IP addresses every so often (default 2 seconds) and display the latency over time as
different colored characters. It’s simple and effective at looking for problems on a medium-size
network like this. Since our network runs almost all MikroTik networking gear, I also made heavy use
of MikroTik WinBox for configuring radios and routers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-02-cping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the race went mostly without a hitch. Toward the afternoon we started getting some
thunderstorms, and that caused me to pack up my personal belongings and leave the site unattended
earlier than I expected, and also caused the Windy Peak checkpoint folks to pack up before a couple
of the runners made it. But we kept accountability of everyone and accomplished our mission, which
in turn allowed the runners to have fun and made the event a success. That’s all we can ask for!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30 Build Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30 Build Day" /><published>2022-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flyclipart.com/concept-map-diagram-network-icon-network-icon-png-83003&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/concept-map-diagram-network-icon-83003.png&quot; alt=&quot;Network Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the day in Evergreen helping with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dirty30.org/&quot;&gt;Dirty 30&lt;/a&gt; communications dry
run. We set up the comms trailer, all 5 aid stations and checkpoints, and the network center point
at City Lights Ridge. This is a critical day every year to make sure we have everything connected
and ready to deploy the day before the race. A couple of the sites have to be hiked into the
mountains, so making sure all of the gear is present and working is incredibly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I focused on City Lights Ridge since I’m going to be stationed there again during the race. It’s not
the most complex site, but because it’s the network’s central point, it talks to pretty much all of
the other sites. It needs to be set up early and run smoothly. Hopefully the work I did today will
ensure success at the race.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LARCfest</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LARCfest" /><published>2022-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fairgrounds.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Boulder County Fairgrounds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it down to &lt;a href=&quot;https://w0eno.org/&quot;&gt;Longmont Amateur Radio Club&lt;/a&gt;’s annual-once-again swapfest. I
took my youngest daughter who had a marvelous time running around, greeting all of the vendors and
looking at all of the bits and bobs. I didn’t find any treasures, but it was great to get some
eyeball QSOs with folks I hadn’t seen in a while. I’m glad these events are finally starting again!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Transmission via Radio</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Transmission via Radio" /><published>2022-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier today I was one of the presenters at another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/&quot;&gt;RMHAM&lt;/a&gt; University
session: Data Transmission via Radio. I joined John W0VG, Willem AC0KQ and Gary WB5PJB in talking
about the Winlink email ecosystem from many different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was given the task of figuring out how to talk about protocols in an understandable way, and I
hope I did the topic justice. I also had a chance to talk about my favorite little Winlink client,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://getpat.io&quot;&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, anyone who keeps up with my dealings knows that I’m a regular
contributor to Pat, and it was great to sing its virtues to another crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/queen-elizabeth-donald-trump.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Donald Trump standing in front of Queen Elizabeth II&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Videos of all of the sessions have been posted to YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RDUPjlm1LSs&quot;&gt;Gary Sutton WB5PJB - Basic Winlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oiqAAfBgPCo&quot;&gt;Chris Keller K0SWE - Winlink Protocols and Pat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iLtap7mNnyU&quot;&gt;John Maxwell W0VG - RMS Trimode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LCItApXlPPo&quot;&gt;Willem Schreuder AC0KQ - BPQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Earlier today I was one of the presenters at another RMHAM University session: Data Transmission via Radio. I joined John W0VG, Willem AC0KQ and Gary WB5PJB in talking about the Winlink email ecosystem from many different angles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box Presentation</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box Presentation" /><published>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-11-winlink-in-a-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winlink in a Box&lt;/strong&gt; is complete, at least as a first iteration. And just in time; I’m going to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1UEEDvDSZwf8X8w8VF07k1LM9I49G5oY94te-oSxsug8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;present&lt;/a&gt;
it tomorrow at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/rocky-mountain-ham-university/&quot;&gt;RMHAM University&lt;/a&gt; Nerdfest.
[Edit: here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fSGivCXoU_0&quot;&gt;video link&lt;/a&gt;!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-12-winlink-in-a-box-inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box inside&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-01-15-ARES-pod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ARES Pod&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncarc.net/&quot;&gt;NCARC&lt;/a&gt; Winter Hamfest up in Loveland, Colorado, and the first
in-person hamfest locally in a good long while. Even with masking and whatnot, it was wonderful to
be back in person to see folks. I spent most of my time at talks. I got a proper introduction to
amateur television from Jim KH6HTV, and that looks like something I’ll have to play with soon! I
also really enjoyed an EmComm talk from Jim AD0ZM, and was particularly interested in the
communications pod he had on display. Sure, I’ve seen pods like it before, but I was reminded that
one of the really nice points about them is that it simplifies setup onsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Jim’s EmComm talk got me back in the thought process of working on Pat integration with VARA.
Pat is sorely lacking VARA support which limits its utility to EmComm folks, and the project has
been languishing. Seeing the pod got me thinking about the reasons I’ve been dragging my feet with
the VARA integration. One of my biggest excuses (for excuse it is) is that setting up both the RMS
station to test against as well as the client station is a lot of toil. It’s not that hard, but it
takes a lot of connecting wires, booting programs and tuning gain levels before I can even start
making any headway. And because I don’t have a lot of space, I inevitably have to take the whole
thing apart within a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my next (hopefully quick) project to springboard me back into Pat+VARA is going to be &lt;strong&gt;Winlink
in a Box&lt;/strong&gt;. I want to take an HT, a soundcard interface and a Raspberry Pi and semi-permanently fix
them in an ammo can. The can should have a power plug on one end, an antenna port on the other, and
it should just work when I power it on. Seal it up so I don’t have to touch the gain knobs, set all
of the software programs to start on boot, and go from zero to working Winlink RMS on VHF VARA FM
within about 60 seconds. All of my work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/pipat&quot;&gt;PiPat&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago will
help, although I’ll no longer be relying on the TNC-Pi. The TNC-Pi only works for AX.25, and for my
purpose I need VARA FM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>