<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-08T01:42:17+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30 testing</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30 testing" /><published>2020-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-VT6KBUPj5_Q/XtZz37eE6VI/AAAAAAABvlo/hgmsz1SFzzsNDdyJ7rmX0yoavmSU7r-KACK4BGAsYHg/s1600/IMG_20200530_095536.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Custom LoRa remote control relays&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today would have been the day of the annual Golden Gate Dirty 30, had COVID-19 not invaded our
lives. The race didn’t happen, but a couple of us from RMHAM decided to head into Golden Gate Canyon
State Park anyway to test out a new apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the problems we experienced in 2019 was a loss of power at City Lights Ridge, a central point
in the temporary IP-over-microwave network that we set up every year. Rather than haul extra
batteries up the hill, we were looking for a creative way to use power more efficiently, and a
couple of folks came up with a solution. Using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/3079&quot;&gt;Adafruit Feather LoRa 433 MHz modules&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/2923&quot;&gt;latching relay FeatherWings&lt;/a&gt;, they built a remote power
control system which would allow them to switch off the network gear when not in use. (I can take no
credit for actually helping with development of the system.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-exCn_dKLGPo/XtZ0SafO3SI/AAAAAAABvl8/-vjqcVza9j8OVMt3GZGhTPq5lM9btoSPACK4BGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200530_095542.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Custom LoRa remote control&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal today was to test propagation and see if they would actually reach where we needed. I hiked
up to City Lights Ridge with a relay module and a remote control; Ben &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KC2VJW&lt;/code&gt; went up Windy Peak
with the same, and Willem &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AC0KQ&lt;/code&gt; started testing with a remote control from near the Tallman
Ranch (which is Aid 1/4 during the race). It took a bit of fiddling with the relay module, but after
resetting it, it did start switching. Willem then hiked down to the Nott Creek Trailhead
(start/finish) and Red Barn. Unfortunately, when I was fiddling with the reset button I apparently
broke the antenna mount solder connections, and by the time Willem made it to start/finish we had a
threatening rain cloud moving in, so we didn’t get a thorough test from Red Barn to City Lights.
However, start/finish to Windy was working well, so that tells us that this LoRa system does have
good propagation even through hilly terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, it was good to get outside and play radio. Most (not all) folks on the trail were
being respectful of social distancing and wearing masks, but the parking lots were quite crowded. I
was glad we got an early start.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">K3NG keyer complete!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/25/k3ng.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="K3NG keyer complete!" /><published>2020-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/25/k3ng</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/25/k3ng.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-fzorERod85Q/XtZqNLRbd4I/AAAAAAABvlU/mm7tlJkDliIF2wb6FU9KzuTroprkHvkngCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200525_235320.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finished K3NG keyer project&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/02/pcb-design.html&quot;&gt;fussing&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/19/pcb-troubleshooting.html&quot;&gt;fiddling&lt;/a&gt;, my custom K3NG Morse keyer with
an Arduino shield PCB is complete! As input, it can accept a straight key, paddles with a knob for
speed control, or the Winkeyer computer interface; for output, it has a side-tone speaker with a
headphone bypass and volume knob, and a separate transceiver output port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be used as a code practice oscillator, an automatic keyer, or a Winkeyer interface. It’s
somewhat redundant as an automatic keyer because most modern radios have that built-in, but it would
still help in keeping both a straight key and paddles plugged in simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a super complex device, but it was a good opportunity to learn more complex circuits than
just “microcontroller pin goes to component,” PCB design, and now I have a dedicated practice
oscillator and Winkeyer interface. I’m happy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PCB arrived, but…</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/19/pcb-troubleshooting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PCB arrived, but…" /><published>2020-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/19/pcb-troubleshooting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/19/pcb-troubleshooting.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-RZOVvqiJ5hg/XsP2YeQi_TI/AAAAAAABvYE/pvzIZE-myWQaGT6_UUHID-G22dysdVW1gCPcBGAYYCw/s320/IMG_20200518_162337.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Unpopulated custom PCB on an Arduino&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news: my PCBs arrived! The bad news: they don’t work, at least not out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was super excited to get my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/02/pcb-design&quot;&gt;custom K3NG keyer boards&lt;/a&gt; in the
mail! I spent some time soldering components last night, but found that it wasn’t working. My first
clue was that there is no Morse code “HI” on the sidetone speaker, nor do the paddles do anything.
The serial port Winkeyer seems to work, so the Arduino is functioning. Then I tried plugging the
transceiver output into an external practice oscillator and found that it was always grounded. Huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-dFC1vXyiH-o/XsP4NFrPH_I/AAAAAAABvYY/LOYBnpwSIbURwyQ1kBUnN5b9G9XQxjFwgCPcBGAYYCw/s320/IMG_20200518_221735.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spaghetti mess of wires&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I found the culprit. Can you spot it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-1qBz5eqmsdg/XsP2ezlN_RI/AAAAAAABvX8/JSdexK9tlYkOqmjHLQ8ecJSBNz07XVqGgCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200518_222441.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sparkfun transistor kit box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-a-HAZ-kL4Bg/XsP2iLMBsxI/AAAAAAABvYA/ydUswpjlQ5InseVjdH4ch5QBMb5na0H_wCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200518_222500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;KiCad transistor footprint&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KiCad footprint has the transistor pins in a different order than the transistors I have. The
base, collector and emitter are out of order. Lesson learned: attention to detail, don’t trust
KiCad’s footprints to be perfect for your parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another mistake, I chose resistor footprints that were exactly as long as my components, but the
resistor leads don’t bend that sharply and so the resistors don’t sit flat. Minor annoyance to fix
next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since these are through-hole parts, I think I can desolder the incorrect transistors and finagle new
transistors with longer legs into the as-designed holes. I looked briefly for different transistors
that would match my board’s pin-out but didn’t immediately see them, and it would take time to order
those. For prototyping’s sake, I want to work around this problem quickly and see if the board works
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Made my first custom PCB</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/02/pcb-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Made my first custom PCB" /><published>2020-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/02/pcb-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/02/pcb-design.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-zlQkC2VI79E/Xq2MmNnx6MI/AAAAAAABu5E/UI2_9SUXesEKxrwkl8xMcLZJldQTPaMJACLcBGAsYHQ/s320/K3NG-keyer-K0SWE-v2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Custom printed circuit board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been interested in hobby electronics longer than amateur radio. I picked up an Arduino
Duemilanove in about 2010 and enjoyed messing around with LEDs, motors and servos. I even designed
(but didn’t complete) a “Weasley Clock” that would take me and my wife’s locations from Google
Latitude (when that was still a thing), translate it into one of about a dozen discrete locations
like “home,” “school” or “work,” and turn stepper motors to display those locations on the hands of
a clock. I had the electronics and the software, but never really figured out the mechanical aspects
of attaching the steppers to my clock’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, fast forward. About 6 months ago I was
&lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2019/10/10/cw&quot;&gt;messing around&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k3ng/k3ng_cw_keyer/wiki/210-Build:-Schematic&quot;&gt;K3NG Morse keyer design&lt;/a&gt;. I built
a basic one on a breadboard, but decided at that time to purchase a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hamprojects.info/mortty/&quot;&gt;Mortty&lt;/a&gt; kit for its size. I still like the Mortty and if I end up
doing CW work in the field I’ll probably use it for that. However, I’ve recently been back to
learning Morse code, and moving around the Mortty box, a separate code practice oscillator and the
heavy Bencher paddles has been awkward. I wanted to revisit more fully featured variants of the K3NG
design that include built-in sidetone, and it’d be fun to have one that would function as an HID
“keyboard” input for a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rebuilt the breadboard and started thinking about building it on a proto-shield, but figured there
was enough complexity to lay it out beforehand in CAD. I’d played
with &lt;a href=&quot;https://fritzing.org/&quot;&gt;Frtizing&lt;/a&gt;
before, mainly for documenting breadboard projects, but that was being cantankerous with the audio
jacks I was trying to use. I decided to switch to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kicad-pcb.org/&quot;&gt;KiCad&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m very
glad I did! It’s certainly got a learning curve and some quirks, but after watching a handful of
YouTube videos (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PlDOnSHkX2c&quot;&gt;overall workflow&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A4_wqnzKZq4&amp;amp;t=650s&quot;&gt;using Arduino template&lt;/a&gt;) and some other
references, I was able to start with an Arduino shield template, bang together a logical schematic,
do footprint mappings, and lay out the PCB in the course of a long evening. And of course, once it’s
in CAD, you &lt;em&gt;might as well&lt;/em&gt; send it off to a fabricator instead of doing in on protoboard, right?
This size Arduino shield was about $25 for 3 boards at OSH Park, which definitely compensates for
hours of cursing at protoboard and looks much nicer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still planning to use an enclosure with a bunch of panel-mount components rather than using
PCB-mounted components. I have 10 panel-mount components, so I’ll have to get good at crimping
Dupont header connectors. Now that I have this feather in my cap, maybe I can look at PCB-mount
components and slide-in extruded enclosures in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Passed my Extra exam!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/26/extra.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passed my Extra exam!" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/26/extra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/26/extra.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.needpix.com/rsynced_images/news-677409_1280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Newspaper with Extra&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very excited to announce that I passed the Element 4 exam to earn an Amateur Extra license! It
took a bit of doing because most places in the US are still shut down due to COVID-19. However, I
kept my ears open and found a completely remote session administered by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://glaarg.org/&quot;&gt;GLAARG VEC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GLAARG has all of their remote exam sessions advertised through
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hamstudy.org/&quot;&gt;HamStudy.org&lt;/a&gt;. A few days ago I registered there and received a PIN and some
instructions right off the bat, with a couple more emails to follow. I tried to read and follow all
the instructions as carefully as I could. In my case, the video conference would be done over Zoom.
They had guidelines about choosing an uncluttered and quiet space, and making sure that nothing
would distract or interrupt me during the exam. They also called for a clean desk, so I took my
station apart to make sure there wouldn’t be a last-minute scramble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning, I logged into Zoom about an hour before the exam. All the test takers, all ~40 of us,
were told to log in around the same time in order to maximize the volunteer examiners’ time, even
though only 2-3 of us could take the exam at once. Everyone not taking the exam waited around in the
Zoom waiting room plus an extra chat room, listening as one of the leads occasionally updated us
about the queue. From me logging in before the test to when it was my turn took about 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it was my turn, I was invited to the main Zoom chat, where my ID was pre-screened. After that,
the host moved me to one of the breakout rooms which consisted of only myself and 5 proctors,
presumably all VEs. I was asked to show my ID again and then turn the camera to show my desk and the
view behind my monitor. After that, the VE took control of my computer screen and logged into the
exam website on my behalf. Then all the proctors turned off their video and mics, leaving me to do
the test. My face and screen were visible to the proctors the whole time. After I hit the submit
button, the proctors turned their mics and cameras back on, and after the lead VE took control again
and confirmed the results, my passing score was displayed immediately! The proctors all
congratulated me, I saved a PDF copy of the test results in place of the usual CSCE, and that was
it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today there are no more GLAARG sessions listed because the test protocol was still considered
somewhat experimental, but they sound very positive and serious about moving forward. Now that they
are satisfied with their methods of maintaining integrity, they can start streamlining the waiting
room process, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking in the near future to take an online ham license exam, I can highly recommend
GLAARG’s sessions. Those sessions are listed through &lt;a href=&quot;https://hamstudy.org/&quot;&gt;HamStudy.org&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s
worth pointing out that GLAARG is using ExamTools which is the same layout as the practice tests
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://hamstudy.org/&quot;&gt;HamStudy.org&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re about to take a test that uses ExamTools, it’s
worth running through practice tests there to get the feel of the real thing. One final thought: do
run through practice exams, because there are plenty available. All the US amateur license exam
questions and answers are published so all the apps have the same questions, and if you’re passing
those practice tests with 90% or better consistently, you’ll know you’re ready. Don’t waste your VE
team’s time if you don’t know whether you’re going to pass, especially while online tests are still
in their infancy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">KE0OG Answer!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/24/ke0og.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KE0OG Answer!" /><published>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/24/ke0og</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/24/ke0og.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-k6pC1oV0gyM/XqL7cvX7PJI/AAAAAAABu0A/QZXA9NHJqwYCRCPC-kXDMzRViw2i4qMTwCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/ke0og.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Dave Casler KE0OG on YouTube&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been following
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaBtYooQdmNzq63eID8RaLQ&quot;&gt;Dave Casler &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KE0OG&lt;/code&gt;’s&lt;/a&gt; YouTube videos
since I started ham radio. (Which was only a year ago, but still…) I really appreciate his pacing
and style: many hams on YouTube have developed a more flashy, fast-talking flair, but sometimes they
feel like click-bait and can get overwhelming to watch. With Dave, it feels like I’m sitting in the
shack learning something from my Elmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On yesterday’s live-stream, Dave
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d1UXHGLYZZk&amp;amp;t=4103&quot;&gt;answered my question&lt;/a&gt; about FT8! I noticed that
the radio transmits much more power if I use an FT8 slot around 2,000 Hz than if I use 300 Hz, and
Dave pointed out that the normal SSB audio bandwidth only accepts audio frequencies between around
400 to 2,500 Hz. He didn’t say this, but it made me realize that I can change the dial frequency to
effectively access those lower and higher FT8 slots, and that I really only have a little over 2 kHz
of useful transmit bandwidth. Good advice, thank you!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting the hang of FT8</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/18/getting-the-hang-of-ft8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting the hang of FT8" /><published>2020-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/18/getting-the-hang-of-ft8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/18/getting-the-hang-of-ft8.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-CNJQPPbh_00/Xpu8C2NvchI/AAAAAAABuuw/7PMKH15ak-Mxm6YaxMWM7gsUakW1zAE_gCPcBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200418_201405.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Radio and computer on a desk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working quite a bit of FT8 on HF in the past few weeks. Without too much effort, I’ve
already collected about 170 QSOs (contacts) with 110 QSLs (confirmed by the other side). Among those
QSLs, I’ve worked 35 states and 4 countries beyond the US, which is pretty incredible to me! My
humble HF station is far from ideal, but it’s doing the job, at least operating FT8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still operating the IC-718 and the EMCOMM II antenna with the IT-100 tuner, SignaLink and CI-V
interfaces. I’ve added an MFJ-822 power/SWR meter, which is actually giving me much different power
numbers than the radio and I’m glad to have it. I’ve learned a lot about what works and doesn’t work
in this particular arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, in the first week or so of operating, I had frequent CI-V resets when raising my
transmit power above 20W. Turns out, the EMCOMM II (as with many end-fed wire antennas) uses the
feedline’s coax as a counterpoise if there’s nothing else, which introduces RF into one’s shack and
wreaks havoc on computer data wires. Adding an independent counterpoise wire helped a lot: on 20m
and above I can use all 100W the radio generates, although I still have the same resetting problem
on 40m and below if I use too much power. I suspect having the antenna 3 feet away from the radio
(through the exterior wall) isn’t helping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things considered, I’m impressed with the current setup. With a starter radio and “temporary”
antenna, I’m approaching a Worked All States award. Still, there’s plenty to improve, like
establishing a station ground and devising some other antenna situation. I’m currently getting a
pretty constant S7 of noise, and I have to wonder if that’s what has foiled my couple of attempts at
ARDOP Winlink. I’m sure I’ll figure that out soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First FT8 contact!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/02/ft8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First FT8 contact!" /><published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/02/ft8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/04/02/ft8.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-v6w8SohYcFU/Xoa4L3nqyMI/AAAAAAABuiI/MykznfqEQsInY-h2_FB9T0R13ldZgRGVwCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/ft8.png&quot; alt=&quot;WSJT-X display&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After setting up my HF station over the weekend, I’ve been dying to try digital modes with it. I’d
heard of FT-8 from several sources as being a relatively easy and fun mode to get into, so I ordered
the necessary cable to go with my SignaLink USB and got working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a little challenging to get everything set up. I already had a CI-V cable I used over the
weekend, which can let the computer query and change the radio’s parameters like frequency, mode,
filters and noise reduction. However, I also needed the second connection with the SignaLink to
receive and send audio. That’s all a bit harder with Linux’s idiosyncrasies with regard to multiple
audio sources and sinks. Add to that the minor headache of compiling WSJT-X from source before
realizing it was available pre-compiled in the Ubuntu APT repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after much fiddling and tweaking, I was able to make my first HF digital mode contact over
FT-8: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;K9IJ&lt;/code&gt; in Illinois, at a distance of 895 miles (1,441 km)! It took me a minute to realize there
was more to an FT-8 QSO than one call/response exchange, and I’ll need to read up on what exactly we
said to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FT-8 has been somewhat controversial in the ham community since it came to prominence a few years
ago. The information exchanged is extremely limited, basically just callsigns and signal strength
reports, which annoys proponents of ham radio’s more extroverted facets like rag-chewing. I believe
one of the things that keeps ham radio relevant is its emergency communication aspects, and I have
to admit, FT-8 doesn’t really check that box. You’re not going to use FT-8 to call in the cavalry
after a natural disaster. Still, it’s an interesting propagation experiment, and a nice
low-commitment way of making QSOs. I understand there are even contests which allow FT-8. If I’m
feeling more chatty, there are other, more conversational digital modes which I’m planning to
explore, and there’s always voice and CW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the thing: amateur radio modes might fade from the limelight, but I can’t think of any mode
that’s been mainstream at some point and then been abandoned. We still use CW and AM and SSB and
simplex FM and RTTY and SSTV and AX.25. Even when “better” things like IP-over-microwave come along,
we haven’t given up on any of these things.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Playing with MikroTiks</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/31/mikrotik.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Playing with MikroTiks" /><published>2020-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/31/mikrotik</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/31/mikrotik.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XnO9SpgXpjg/XoTR2C5WbJI/AAAAAAABufY/QsMXAiZ6XlIw8zHgoAXi2MhvvQzAK8zoQCKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200401_112827.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MikroTik networking gear&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an effort to jog my memory from last December’s RMHAM networking workshop, I decided to set up a
miniature lab of my own. I’m glad I did, because even a simple arrangement had me scratching my head
for a while!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two MikroTik LHGs, two hEX PoE lites, and two laptops, and the goal was to get those
configured to ping from one side to the other and back via Part 97 frequencies with RMHAM’s
conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial setup went well enough. One wrinkle is that I run Linux on almost all of my computers,
and run MikroTik’s Winbox client using a Wine compatibility layer. That’s fine, but I also use UFW
as a firewall, which interferes with Winbox’s ability to scan for neighbors or connect by MAC
address. I had to remember to turn off UFW while doing this experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I was trying to power the LHGs using the hEX routers and avoid even more cable spaghetti by
using separate PoE injectors. This meant that I couldn’t plug directly into the LHGs; when I
mis-configured them and needed to get back in by MAC, I had to add their port to the hEX router’s
bridge temporarily. Seems like a sneaky kludge, but it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the MikroTik LHG radios to use the ham band, they have to be the “international” version.
After that, you can use the “superchannel” selection to change the available frequencies and move to
the ham band. RMHAM usually uses their club callsign &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N0SZ&lt;/code&gt; as part of the 802.11 SSID so that every
packet transmitted has station identification per Part 97, so I followed suit and used my own
callsign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the last step I was still having trouble; my pings between the laptops were only getting halfway
through the network. The radios could ping each other, but the routers weren’t working together.
Finally, I took the radios out since they were bridging and therefore just a fancy ethernet cable,
and plugged the routers directly together. The problem persisted, and I found that my static route
gateways were set to forward by interface, not to their neighbor’s IP. Once I fixed that, the
traffic started flowing, and kept flowing after reintroducing the radios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t touch OSPF this time around, and I don’t know that two routers is enough to do a meaningful
experiment, but I should refresh myself on that as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First HF contact!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/29/first-hf-qso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First HF contact!" /><published>2020-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/29/first-hf-qso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/03/29/first-hf-qso.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-e7H_uTwK9IM/XoTcCH760TI/AAAAAAABufo/_JozWp9qGegZwfspkYEKrRxif5LTmKCVACKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200325_183420.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chameleon EMCOMM II transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being stuck at home during the COVID-19 pandemic, I finally had occasion to set up an HF antenna. I
picked up a relatively inexpensive and flexible Chameleon EMCOMM II. My “shack” is a 2nd story guest
bedroom/home office, so I set up the transformer directly outside the window and ran the wire out to
the backyard in a top-fed sloper configuration. I set that up with the Icom IC-718 I got from Dick
and Alan’s SK collection, and the LDG IT-100 tuner I picked up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend happened to be a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cqwpx.com/&quot;&gt;CQ WPX&lt;/a&gt; SSB contest. That meant that there
was plenty of activity, but it was a little intimidating to jump in and attempt to make contacts. I
finally overcame my mic fright and made my first HF QSO: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KK9A&lt;/code&gt; in North Carolina, at a distance of
1,377 miles (2,217 km). He heard me, I heard him; unfortunately, I don’t know if I made the contest
exchange correctly, because he moved on quickly. Still, I’m happy that my HF station is working!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried several more QSOs during the contest, but wasn’t acknowledged by anyone else. My receive has
a constant S7 of noise and I know my antenna positioning up close to the house is not ideal. Also,
some coworkers mentioned that the solar inverters on my house and my neighbor’s are notoriously
noisy, but might be mitigated. I’m sure there are more adjustments to make before I’ll be heard
reliably.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>