<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-20T03:25:35+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Starting with SATRAN</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/11/25/rotator.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting with SATRAN" /><published>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/11/25/rotator</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/11/25/rotator.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/satran-grey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SATRAN&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back in 2019 I got an &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/22/amsat-ariss.html&quot;&gt;introduction to AMSAT&lt;/a&gt;,
and have been interested in making contacts ever since. I picked up an Arrow antenna,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/04/baby-steps-toward-ariss.html&quot;&gt;collected some telemetry&lt;/a&gt;, and even
tried making QSOs once, but the extreme level of multitasking was overwhelming. The one thing I’ve
been really keen to automate has been tracking: keeping the antenna pointed at the satellite
throughout its pass. Automating that part requires an azimuth-elevation (az/el) rotator. The most
well-known option for that is the Yaesu G-5500 rotator which retails new for about $700, too
expensive to justify using once or twice while I see if I enjoy working AMSAT regularly. I’ve kept
my eyes open for lighter-weight options, and one that stuck out was &lt;a href=&quot;https://satran.io&quot;&gt;SATRAN&lt;/a&gt; by
Daniel Nikolajsen, SM7YSA. For a while, it was sold as a kit, but mainly in Europe and explicitly
not to the US or Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it seems SATRAN is no longer being sold as a kit, but the plans to build it are available, so
I’ve finally decided to build my own. Daniel published pretty much everything necessary to get it
going: STL files to 3D print the enclosure, Gerber files to order PCBs, scale drawings to cut sheet
metal parts, and firmware code. I’ve spent some time reverse-engineering which electrical components
need to go on the PCBs, as well as started prepping and 3D printing the housing. For the two sheet
metal parts, there’s a service called OSH Cut that I think I’ll try. They seem to be tangentially
related to OSH Park who I’ve used in the past for PCBs. However, Daniel only published PDF printable
templates, not DXF CAD drawings, so I’ll have to redraw those in CAD to be able to send them off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might take a while to gather all of the different bits and pieces of this project, but I think it
will be rewarding to put together, especially if it gives me a workable AMSAT tool in the end!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Field Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/06/26/field-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field Day" /><published>2023-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/06/26/field-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/06/26/field-day.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m just coming back from another fabulous Field Day spent with RMHAM! Words hardly do the event
justice, so take a look at some of the pictures!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-23_19-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hanging out in the afternoon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-24_13-35.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kaylee on GOTA with me&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-24_19-07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kaylee on GOTA with Lisa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-25_08-33.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QRV with the FT8 station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-25_09-34.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Satellite station with the bunk trailer in the background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-26_21-17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ava and I taking a sunset stroll&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-06-24-field-day-crew.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The whole RMHAM Field Day crew&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my family’s first RV trip, so we rented from Cruise America and had a wonderful time. This
was also my first time taking the entire clan up to Field Day. I got all of them on the Get On The
Air (GOTA) station to make a few contacts, and my older daughter is seriously hooked! She made
almost 30 QSOs and probably would have kept going if there had been time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit: John W0VG posted a video, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hXDzzWUICxc&quot;&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m just coming back from another fabulous Field Day spent with RMHAM! Words hardly do the event justice, so take a look at some of the pictures!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Catalog Progress</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/05/26/catalog-progress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Catalog Progress" /><published>2023-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/05/26/catalog-progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/05/26/catalog-progress.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been plugging away at the &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/29/catalog.html&quot;&gt;ARES Catalog&lt;/a&gt; project. After negotiating
some clearer requirements, I set out building a prototype with &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextjs.org/&quot;&gt;Next.JS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the database, I started out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.postgresql.org/&quot;&gt;Postgres&lt;/a&gt; using the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prisma.io/nextjs&quot;&gt;Prisma&lt;/a&gt; library. I experimented at first with writing my own Next.JS
server-side API, then using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/premieroctet/next-crud&quot;&gt;Next-CRUD&lt;/a&gt; to generate the
API. Ultimately, I abandoned this whole line of development because I realized that Postgres was
costing me too much money for a scale-to-zero project. Since then, I switched the Next.JS app to use
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt; via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mongoosejs.com/&quot;&gt;Mongoose&lt;/a&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app’s core functionality has been coming along. I’ve imported the ICS 217s from Ben’s
spreadsheets into the database and can display those, both in nice web tables as well as a printable
view that closely matches the printed forms. Still, I can’t help but feel like my progress has been
much slower trying to learn React than if I’d stayed in my comfort zone with Angular. React just
hasn’t “clicked” for me yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been plugging away at the ARES Catalog project. After negotiating some clearer requirements, I set out building a prototype with Next.JS.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES Catalog</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/29/catalog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES Catalog" /><published>2023-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/29/catalog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/29/catalog.html">&lt;p&gt;It seems I’ve been roped into another project. Colorado ARES section leaders want to create a
catalog of important information for use by ARES groups across the state. It will include things
like ICS 217s describing all of the repeaters and channels used by each group, ICS 205s to break
those channels down per-event, and ICS 205As with contact information of event personnel. I’ve been
tasked with creating a web application to collect and display this information. I’m just one of
several people working on this project, but I’m the only one with web development experience. Ben
KB0UBZ is technically savvy and is willing to help collect and massage data. Our subject matter
experts are Joe KD0TYU and Randy N0OEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we’re really trying to narrow down exactly what we’re trying to build in the first
place. Willem AC0KQ pitched this project to me as somthing to fill out complete Incident Action
Plans with many ICS forms, but Joe and Randy’s vision for this as a catalog is quite different. I
think we’ll start with the bare minimum, just publishe ICS 217s organized by ARES group, and then
build from there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It seems I’ve been roped into another project. Colorado ARES section leaders want to create a catalog of important information for use by ARES groups across the state. It will include things like ICS 217s describing all of the repeaters and channels used by each group, ICS 205s to break those channels down per-event, and ICS 205As with contact information of event personnel. I’ve been tasked with creating a web application to collect and display this information. I’m just one of several people working on this project, but I’m the only one with web development experience. Ben KB0UBZ is technically savvy and is willing to help collect and massage data. Our subject matter experts are Joe KD0TYU and Randy N0OEM.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grandstream Phone</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/18/grandstream.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grandstream Phone" /><published>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/18/grandstream</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/18/grandstream.html">&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to my &lt;a href=&quot;/2023/03/03/pbx.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; on IP phones, I picked up a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00VNMWRFK/&quot;&gt;Grandstream GXP1625&lt;/a&gt; for still pretty cheap. Let me
tell you how much easier it was to set up with both FreePBX and Hamshack Hotline! The phone has a
web interface, and it was a breeze to configure. I didn’t have to mess with XML files or TFTP
servers. I pointed the phone at Hamshack Hotline and my own experimental FreePBX server, and it just
worked. So much easier than the Cisco phone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As a follow-up to my previous post on IP phones, I picked up a Grandstream GXP1625 for still pretty cheap. Let me tell you how much easier it was to set up with both FreePBX and Hamshack Hotline! The phone has a web interface, and it was a breeze to configure. I didn’t have to mess with XML files or TFTP servers. I pointed the phone at Hamshack Hotline and my own experimental FreePBX server, and it just worked. So much easier than the Cisco phone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting started with Hamshack Hotline and FreePBX</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/03/pbx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting started with Hamshack Hotline and FreePBX" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/03/pbx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/03/03/pbx.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve used VoIP a couple of times in conjuction with ham radio for supporting public events; some
troubleshooting problems lend themselves to full duplex communication better than PTT radios. Until
now I hadn’t really considered setting up something for myself, but then I learned about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hamshackhotline.com/&quot;&gt;Hamshack Hotline&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a collective of VoIP geeks running their own
phone network, and it even has links into RF repeaters and such. Neat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HH keeps a list of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.hamshackhotline.com/doku.php?id=kb:supported.endpoints&quot;&gt;fully supported devices&lt;/a&gt;, but
I was somewhat drawn to an unsupported device, a Cisco 7900 series, for nostalgic reasons (it’s what
I supported in the Army) as well as cost (~$20 on eBay). Because of this, I was directed down the
road of setting up my own local PBX with a trunk connection to HH. How hard could that be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;freepbx-initial-setup&quot;&gt;FreePBX initial setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download https://www.freepbx.org/. I used the ISO image to create a VM for testing. Create an admin
account and do basic configuration.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL1fn6oC5ndU_umAhL9A_1zkC90hMPDPNO&quot;&gt;This YouTube series&lt;/a&gt; goes
in-depth about the entire process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then add some phone extensions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ME1fCwJNes8&quot;&gt;This video on creating extensions&lt;/a&gt;
was particularly useful. I also found it very helpful to register a couple of software phone
clients, which were relatively easy, before moving on to dealing with Cisco “legacy” hardware
issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cisco-7965g-setup&quot;&gt;Cisco 7965G setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cisco-7965.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cisco 7965&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download
&lt;a href=&quot;https://software.cisco.com/download/home/281346596/type/282074288/release/9.4(2)SR3&quot;&gt;SIP Firmware&lt;/a&gt;.
You need SIP firmware. Some folks advise to use v8 or v9, but both worked for me. You need the
“firmware files only” zip file. Unzip the files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The firmware files need to be served by a TFTP server. I used &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tftpd-hap&lt;/code&gt; on my workstation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your DHCP server needs to advertise the TFTP server. My DHCP server is running on my MikroTik
router. At first I tried setting “DHCP option 150,” but that didn’t seem to work; I could see in
MikroTik WinBox that the phone kept rejecting DHCP offers. Instead I set the “next-server” option,
which worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the steps below to factory reset your Cisco IP phone and get it to download the new firmware.
Here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/xcpJFfuSh7g&quot;&gt;good video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unplug the power cable from the IP phone and then plug it back in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While the phone is powering up, and before the speaker button flashes on and off, press and hold
the pound # key.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue to hold # until each line button (right of the LCD screen) flashes on and off in
sequence in orange color.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now release the pound # key and type the following sequence &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;123456789*0#&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(On the first phone I tried, I had a hardware issue: I’d start typing the 123… sequence and the
phone would start booting normally before I could finish. Luckily, I bought two, and the other phone
behaved as intended.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phone should show “Upgrading” and the MAC address on the screen. It will download the firmware
files one by one and show its progress. After the last file is downloaded, the phone will reboot and
the firmware upgrade is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you need to configure the phone by downloading and modifying an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://usecallmanager.nz/sepmac-cnf-xml.html&quot;&gt;XML file&lt;/a&gt;, renaming it to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SEP{MAC_ADDRESS}.cfg.xml&lt;/code&gt;
and putting that on your TFTP server. The XML file at a minimum needs to specify the SIP server
address, username and password. Many other config options are available. As I was iterating on the
config file, I found it useful to modify the value in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;phoneLabel&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so I could easily tell if the
phone had downloaded my latest version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, I was stuck for a while with the Cisco phone unable to register with the FreePBX
server despite having picked up its configuration file. I found advice to find the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;force_rport&lt;/code&gt;
setting within FreePBX/Asterisk for that phone’s extension advanced settings and turn that setting
“off”; that made it so I could call out from the Cisco phone, but was unable to receive calls. I
also tried enabling TCP for the Asterisk server and forcing that extension to use it; still no dice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the story takes a turn for the worse: I asked for advice from some of my ham friends,
some of whom are VoIP professionals, and their advice was to abandon all hope. Cisco phones are
apparently very nice in an enterprise setting with their proprietary controller, but are not really
suitable for hobbyists. Yes, they can be made to work, but are not worth the time to set up and keep
running. It’s better, my friends say, to use a desk phone that will work without putting up a fight.
So I guess I’ll try out a Polycom or a Grandstream or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put many hours into this project, and I still don’t have a working connection to Hamshack
Hotline! I guess I’m getting what I paid for. Still, I’ve learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve used VoIP a couple of times in conjuction with ham radio for supporting public events; some troubleshooting problems lend themselves to full duplex communication better than PTT radios. Until now I hadn’t really considered setting up something for myself, but then I learned about Hamshack Hotline. It’s a collective of VoIP geeks running their own phone network, and it even has links into RF repeaters and such. Neat!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prepping for W1AW/0 Colorado</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/25/w1aw0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prepping for W1AW/0 Colorado" /><published>2023-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/25/w1aw0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/25/w1aw0.html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I was posed a question by some friends who happen to currently be ARRL section
leaders for Colorado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year the ARRL has a special event called Volunteers On The Air, VOTA. As part of that program,
each section will have a couple of week-long blocks at at points through the year to operate with
the callsign “W1AW portable,” which is a very special honor! However, each section needs to organize
their own operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So coming up in May, we need to have skilled Colorado operators lined up to take shifts to operate
as many bands and modes as possible for 7 consecutive days. However, the ARRL didn’t perscribe how
exactly we should manage those logistics. There’s an online tool available that was developed by
another section, but my friends weren’t impressed; it’s sort of a “Contact Us” form with a text
field for the operator’s callsign and dropdowns for their requested date, time, band and mode.
Submitting the form sends the information to who-knows-where, operators have to fill out this form
once for each shift they pick up, and have no visibility as to who else might want to operate at
that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends thought maybe Colorado could come up with something better. And I agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve spent the past few days building a web app basically from scratch, but leveraging some of my
work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/forester&quot;&gt;Forester&lt;/a&gt;. The new app will also be written in Angular
Typescript and use Firebase for storage and cloud functions. The basic idea is for operators to sign
up with an account and get approved by one of the section leaders. Once they’re approved, they can
view the entire shift schedule by day, band and mode. They can see who’s operating around them, and
they can reserve shifts (or cancel) with a single click. And because I’m using Firestore’s realtime
capabilities, users can watch the shifts get reserved and freed up immediately without a page
refresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool is still pretty early in development, but I feel like we’ve already leveled up over what’s
out there. Plus, it’s open-source, so other sections can adopt it if they’re interested. Check out
my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/w1aw-schedule&quot;&gt;W1AW/0 Colorado Scheduler&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A few days ago I was posed a question by some friends who happen to currently be ARRL section leaders for Colorado.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Entry Panel</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/06/entry-panel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Entry Panel" /><published>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/06/entry-panel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2023/02/06/entry-panel.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2023-02-06-entry-panel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Entry panel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/2022/10/15/hiatus.html&quot;&gt;move&lt;/a&gt; has been going well. We’re mostly settled in, and ham-wise I’ve
been able to limp along with a window coax passthrough to my temporary station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I did the scariest thing since
&lt;a href=&quot;/2019/11/02/mobile-antenna.html&quot;&gt;cutting a hole in the roof of my car&lt;/a&gt;: I cut a hole in the side of
my house! I purchased an entry panel from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kf7p.com/KF7P/Welcome.html&quot;&gt;KF7P Metalwerks&lt;/a&gt;,
and it looks excellent. The process of cutting the hole was nerve-wracking, but it went smoothly.
The panel came with a section of conduit, so getting the panel placed correctly and weather sealed
was easy. I’m very happy with the result. I’ll be able to establish a good ground system and run
plenty of cables through the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I ran through was actually an ethernet cable for a microwave hop up to Eldorado
Mountain and directly into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/amateur-microwave-network/&quot;&gt;RMHAM backbone&lt;/a&gt;!
I’ll get my UHF/VHF J-pole and HF long wire set up soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Hiatus</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Hiatus" /><published>2022-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/10/15/hiatus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Moving-boxes.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/moving-boxes.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Moving boxes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My family and I are moving! It’s only a short distance, but it still means I need to take down all
of the permanently installed shack components like my QTH antennas. I’ll have to rely on my mobile
and portable gear for a while. It also means I won’t have much spare time for ham projects until
everything is moved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, Dave Casler just posted a video about a practice that luckily I’ve already
been following: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2TvdvcE2cJQ&quot;&gt;Keep the boxes!&lt;/a&gt; That should make the
move (at least for the shack) a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish us luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Motorola DMR Radios for Hams</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motorola DMR Radios for Hams" /><published>2022-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/09/10/motorola.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that came out of my trip to Westcreek was a renewed interest in getting Motorola
radios to work for myself. I originally became interested in this back in February when RMHAM
University did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aUFTMX7Ys00&quot;&gt;class&lt;/a&gt; on using commercial DMR radios
from Motorola and Kenwood for ham radio purposes. Among other things, the Motorola section of the
class covered the very important difference between using the old and new versions of the customer
programming software (CPS). The class piqued my interest and I picked up a sleek Motorola SL-300 but
didn’t actually get very far programming it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-10-02-moto-sl300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Motorola SL-300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So over the past couple of weeks, I’ve tried to keep track of everything I needed to do to get
licenses for and successfully program one of these Motorola radios. Ultimately I needed to get the
TRBO CPS license as well as a wideband (25khz) entitlement from Motorola. There seems to be a lot of
outdated information out there, so hopefully this will be updated advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, note that the Motorola radio website is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.motorolasolutions.com&quot;&gt;https://www.motorolasolutions.com&lt;/a&gt;; just plain motorola.com is
for the cell phone division. I got an account on motorolasolutions.com, but that only gave me access
to the consumer side with FRS/GMRS/MURS radios. To order the necessary part numbers, I had to
contact customer service and have them upgrade my account to a business account with a 10-digit
customer ID. It sounds like this is a common arrangement for hams. Once they did that, I was able to
access &lt;a href=&quot;https://myview.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;https://myview.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I went on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://learning.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;http://learning.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt; and took training
course &lt;em&gt;PRD0001: FCC Narrowbanding Mandate Training&lt;/em&gt; which carefully explained that wideband FM
channels are no longer allowed on commercial bands, only on ham radio bands. That only took about 15
minutes to complete. After I finished that, I had to again contact customer service and have them
manually verify completion and open up the option to order the 25khz entitlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all of that was done I was able to go back to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.motorolasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;https://shop.motorolasolutions.com/&lt;/a&gt; and order part numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HKVN4362A for the TRBO CPS, which became free in February of 2022&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HKVN4046A for the 25khz entitlement, also free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-09-10-motorola-cart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Motorola Solutions shopping cart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all of this hassle, I was finally able to download the TRBO CPS 2 from MyView, add the
wideband entitlement and program to my heart’s content. I wouldn’t really say I’m happy with CPS 2
because there is no import/export functionality, but considering there’s no other option with
Motorola radios, I guess I’ll just be happy it works at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line here is that when working with Motorola equipment as a ham, don’t expect to be able
to do anything self-service. Contact customer support; it’s relatively quick and painless, and you
won’t get far any other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of the things that came out of my trip to Westcreek was a renewed interest in getting Motorola radios to work for myself. I originally became interested in this back in February when RMHAM University did a class on using commercial DMR radios from Motorola and Kenwood for ham radio purposes. Among other things, the Motorola section of the class covered the very important difference between using the old and new versions of the customer programming software (CPS). The class piqued my interest and I picked up a sleek Motorola SL-300 but didn’t actually get very far programming it.</summary></entry></feed>