<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-08T14:05:27+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Prepare for Countdown!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/12/19/kellog-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prepare for Countdown!" /><published>2020-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/12/19/kellog-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/12/19/kellog-launch.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-XHv7vb7Rwgc/X94esnQ_4LI/AAAAAAAByKs/caJYnhBoNXwEWmOqj48IoZf9_Pa2pOZmgCLcBGAsYHQ/w320-h213/1024px-Amateur_Rocket_Launch_at_Big_Ass_Loading_Lifting_Suckers_%2528BALLS%2529_2017.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rocket launch&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Amateur_Rocket_Launch_at_Big_Ass_Loading_Lifting_Suckers_(BALLS)_2017.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt;
CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m continuing to focus most of my energy on getting KelLog into shape for a public launch. I’m
already using KelLog for my daily logging needs, but there are plenty of sharp corners that need to
be smoothed out before handing it to other people and expecting them to be successful and delighted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, there’s the question of packaging &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kel-agent&lt;/code&gt;. This is the semi-magical program that
allows web applications talk to installed amateur radio programs like WSJT-X. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Kel-agent&lt;/code&gt; needs to
be installed, which means it’s not enough to have an executable that builds; it needs to be copied
into a particular folder on the user’s machine and added to their command line &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt;. This has to
be done separately for each operating system, so I’ve learned more than I ever wanted to know
about &lt;a href=&quot;http://wixtoolset.org/&quot;&gt;WiX&lt;/a&gt; for Windows,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://s.sudre.free.fr/Software/Packages/about.html&quot;&gt;Packages&lt;/a&gt; for Mac, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Debian/dh-make-golang&quot;&gt;dh-make-golang&lt;/a&gt; for Debian. I also found a sponsor to
help me submit &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kel-agent&lt;/code&gt; and its dependencies to the Debian APT repo, so eventually, it will be
available for users of &lt;a href=&quot;https://packages.debian.org/sid/kel-agent&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://packages.ubuntu.com/hirsute/kel-agent&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; and derivatives to install through Linux’s
version of the “app store.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been investing heavily in GitHub Actions automation to make sure that I can sustainably
maintain the 8 (and growing) repositories that make up
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/docs&quot;&gt;KelLog’s complete solution&lt;/a&gt;. I want to make sure that if and when I
start getting bug reports and feature requests, I can focus on writing code and not on some
laborious process for deploying or cutting releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond KelLog, I’ve been getting some requests to step up in two of my ham radio organizations.
First, I’m joining the leadership team of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coaresr1d6.org/&quot;&gt;Colorado ARES R1D6&lt;/a&gt; as their
Training Coordinator. In that role, I’ll be responsible for making sure we have a training plan that
engages and illuminates the entire 45-person team from the newbies to the old hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I’m going to be helping the Rocky Mountain Ham group to launch an extension to their
existing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/rocky-mountain-ham-university/&quot;&gt;RMHAM University&lt;/a&gt;
program, called RMHAM Tech Talks. These are intended to be shorter presentations lasting about an
hour, and will take advantage of RMHAM’s new internet livestream studio.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Wikimedia CC BY-SA 4.0</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">KelLog is becoming useful!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/11/03/kellog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KelLog is becoming useful!" /><published>2020-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/11/03/kellog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/11/03/kellog.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-fb2UqDETuAU/X6Fmso0jobI/AAAAAAABxjI/vrJGqIJYXEEp9qxL-fGEDdOPD2HlQz4JACLcBGAsYHQ/w640-h416/Screenshot%2Bfrom%2B2020-11-03%2B06-44-31.png&quot; alt=&quot;KelLog connected to WSJT-X&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been busy coding on my new contact logging application, and I’m happy to say that it’s becoming
useful enough to use it as my day-to-day logger. What’s more, my employer has released any copyright
claims, so I can now open-source the whole thing! Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forester.radio&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/kellog&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logger consists of a hosted website which syncs almost instantly between machines thanks to
being backed by Firebase. That on its own might not be very interesting, but as I’ve
&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/07/19/grounding.html&quot;&gt;hinted before&lt;/a&gt;, I built a small translator program that lets the
website talk to WSJT-X and can be extended to other radio software. There are some web-based loggers
that can talk to desktop radio software, but the ones I’ve seen have to be served from the same
machine. I think I’ve built something novel: the first &lt;em&gt;hosted&lt;/em&gt; web logger that can talk to desktop
radio software. And I’ve built it to be modular enough that folks can build on what I’ve started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still plenty of missing features and rough edges to work out, but I’m very pleased that
it’s at a point that it’s usable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES Simulated Emergency Test</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/10/04/ares-set.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES Simulated Emergency Test" /><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/10/04/ares-set</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/10/04/ares-set.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-n6_XTRXdtSQ/X3pDmTco7iI/AAAAAAABxMg/0mANuw4yIZ81jgONYlLea76mCI7xaEyuACPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20201003_143109321.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Truck with antennas in the mountains&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a member of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coaresr1d6.org/&quot;&gt;Colorado ARES Region 1 District 6&lt;/a&gt;
team covering Jefferson, Gilpin and Clear Creek counties since January. However, with the pandemic
happening, basically all of our regular served events and in-person training have been cancelled. I
think a few folks have deployed to help with incidents, but there hasn’t been much for newbies to
do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was thrilled yesterday to participate in my first ARES Simulated Emergency Test (SET) exercise.
Our team activated all 3 county Emergency Operation Centers (Clear Creek EOC was virtual from
someone’s house) as well as the City of Lakewood EOC! We had about 8 folks to staff those, and 15
folks out in the field sending pre-arranged “injects” or scenarios. One of the goals was to give the
EOC staff practice at handling and aggregating traffic, and another goal was to test connectivity
from our territory in various places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-q1fdrSFhIZk/X3pDmT7HuZI/AAAAAAABxMg/CkzZ3K5ujvk2fXPLWpxKuSg6CuNhFwaZgCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20201003_143135511.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Truck passenger seat with radios and a laptop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was one of the field operators, and my assignment was up in Rollinsville, CO on the Peak to Peak
Highway. It was a beautiful day for a mountain drive; the fall colors were in full bloom, and the
air was cool and crisp, a nice change from the wildfire smoke we’ve been experiencing. My location
was in a bit of a canyon and the exercise planners were worried it would be a challenging location
to transmit out on UHF. However, a DMR handheld with a mag-mount antenna performed flawlessly and
was able to get out of the canyon to the repeater just fine. I also attempted a VHF packet radio
connection for Winlink, but the RMS was behind several mountains and just couldn’t get out. I wasn’t
too surprised. Maybe next year I’ll have my QRP HF station ready and enough experience to bounce a
Winlink message out of the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello again, H-250!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/13/h250.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello again, H-250!" /><published>2020-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/13/h250</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/13/h250.html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t received my pre-ordered Lab599 Discovery TX-500 yet, but I’m still eagerly awaiting it.
One of the reviews that helped me decide on it came from the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/hoshnasi&quot;&gt;Ham Radio Crash Course&lt;/a&gt; YouTube channel. Josh &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KI6NAZ&lt;/code&gt; got a
preview unit on loan and did a couple of videos. I was inspired when I saw he had gotten an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/CiDgjfGv7TY?t=585&quot;&gt;H-250 military handset with a GX-12 connector&lt;/a&gt; wired for the
TX-500. I felt very nostalgic from using those during my time in the Army Signal Corps, so I decided
to look into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nktPPBhaeLs/X17Y7SZywHI/AAAAAAABw5Y/kzODRhBHOGYGJcKCTmpIPD2SQcssWEP0wCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20200913_180250319.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;H-250 handset adapted to IC-718&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a chap who’s building an entire lineup of accessories for the TX-500,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w2eny.com/tx500/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W2ENY&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I figure that’s probably where Josh got his. After looking
at &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W2ENY&lt;/code&gt;’s shop, I decided I ought to try and source the parts a little cheaper and try building
them myself. I don’t mind paying for quality work, but finishing connectors and building cables
feels like something I should be able to do. Besides, I already have to build a custom cable for the
SignaLink, so I’m already exercising those skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The H-250 with the original military U-229/U connector only runs about $25 on eBay. I could have cut
off the original connector and replaced it with the GX-12 to fit the TX-500, but I decided instead
to pursue making a family of adapter cables. I ordered several U-228/U male connectors, and now I
can build adapter cables to connect a stock H-250 to many of my radios. Since I don’t have the
TX-500 yet, I decided to build the first adapter cable for my Icom IC-718 with a GX-16 connector. So
far in testing, it works great! The handset speaker is clearer than the radio’s front speaker, and
speaking into the mic produces movement on the dummy load power meter. I still need to try it in an
actual QSO; frankly I don’t have much experience yet with HF voice, but this should inspire me to
try it some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next step is to build adapter cables for other radios. I have one planned for the TX-500 of
course, but I figure doing one with the K-1 plug would be fun; that would fit my Anytone D878UV,
Baofeng UV-5R and others. I have this image now of my army pack with one of those foldable tactical
blade antennas that look like the AS-3683A/PRC, that and the H-250 sticking out, and it would look
just like when I was out on an FTX with a SINCGARS manpack. Ah, good times.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I haven’t received my pre-ordered Lab599 Discovery TX-500 yet, but I’m still eagerly awaiting it. One of the reviews that helped me decide on it came from the Ham Radio Crash Course YouTube channel. Josh KI6NAZ got a preview unit on loan and did a couple of videos. I was inspired when I saw he had gotten an H-250 military handset with a GX-12 connector wired for the TX-500. I felt very nostalgic from using those during my time in the Army Signal Corps, so I decided to look into it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking forward to QRP</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/02/looking-to-qrp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking forward to QRP" /><published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/02/looking-to-qrp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/09/02/looking-to-qrp.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.hamradio.com/images_manuf/H0-017255A.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lab599 Discovery TX-500 radio&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work is continuing on my new web-based logger program, but in the meantime I’ve gotten more serious
about putting together a kit for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sota.org.uk/&quot;&gt;SOTA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pota.us/&quot;&gt;POTA&lt;/a&gt;
activations. SOTA combines ham radio with hiking, so everything needs to be rugged, small and
lightweight. Low-power QRP gear is popular in this arena, and I’m excited to have placed a pre-order
for my first QRP transceiver: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lab599.com/&quot;&gt;Lab599&lt;/a&gt; Discovery TX-500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things that exited me about the TX-500 are its SDR architecture, large panadapter display
(something my IC-718 at home doesn’t even have) and extremely durable and water resistant machined
aluminum case. Reviews from folks like Josh &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KI6NAZ&lt;/code&gt; and Julian &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OH8STN&lt;/code&gt; were very informative about
its capabilities and limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have criticized the TX-500 for missing features like a built-in battery, tuner and in-body
speaker. And yeah, if I already owned an Elecraft or Xiegu QRP transceiver, it would be hard to
justify getting this as a second QRP radio. But I really highly prize the water resistance, thermal
considerations and the ruggedness of the case, so I’ll give this a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-fF4DuQjm6KU/X0_DiY40ixI/AAAAAAABwqQ/EZMl0QAWZgkyHK9m95uUxi6vC95UfRODACLcBGAsYHQ/w376-h196/SOTA_POTA%2BStation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring diagram for SignaLink to TX-500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package is supposed to come with most of the necessary cables to adapt the unconventional
water-resistant GX-12 connectors to more standard connectors, like a 3.5mm jack for a CW
key/paddles, and an unterminated power cable. The one cable that doesn’t seem to come in the package
is the audio cable for digital modes, so I’ve taken a little time to plan out how I’m going to build
my own and order parts. The standard audio cable shown in the manual has two 3.5mm plugs for a sound
card; I’m used to using the SignaLink USB, so I’m planning a cable for use with that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Overcoming RF in the shack, the sneaky way</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/08/14/overcoming-rf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overcoming RF in the shack, the sneaky way" /><published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/08/14/overcoming-rf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/08/14/overcoming-rf.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-F7qBed_m_NY/Xzbv2YXIbVI/AAAAAAABwfQ/VvA96kHPb-AyDWsKX9KBvZCS4k_oiF0NQCLcBGAsYHQ/w263-h263/IMG_20200811_083114.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ham radio connected to a Raspberry Pi computer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life has conspired to keep me from doing as much with ham radio lately, but I’m happy to report that
I’m at least back on the air. In my last post I described my troubles with RF getting into the shack
which resets my radio-computer CI-V (CAT) control. I posited that finally setting up a first-class
station ground would help, but alas, I haven’t gotten that far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did find a sneaky solution to my problem. The radio was connected to my desktop computer
with USB extension cords which made the entire USB run about 10 ft. I made those runs shorter, not
by moving anything particular, but by adding a Raspberry Pi single-board computer dedicated to
running the radio. This keeps the USB cords a couple of feet long, and so far it has resolved the
interference that was resetting my CAT control. I can run VNC remote desktop from my main computer
for a similar experience to what I was doing before, but I also now have the option to use a laptop
around the house, which is kind of liberating. The biggest downside of running WSJT-X or other modes
from another room is that my Icom 718 doesn’t give me accurate power and SWR readings, so I have to
do a little bit of guesstimation from experience with my station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially set up a Raspberry Pi 3 B+ I had on hand, but decoding FT8 was slow. When decodes are
showing up 5 seconds into a 15 second transmit period, it’s not effective to respond. Therefore, I
upgraded to an RPi 4 for the first time. I used
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/km4ack/pi-build&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KM4ACK&lt;/code&gt;’s Build-A-Pi&lt;/a&gt; script to set up my RPi software. There
are a few things I’d tweak about it, but overall, it’s extremely nice to have so much ham software
available and preconfigured.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New station setup and grounding problems</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/07/19/grounding.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New station setup and grounding problems" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/07/19/grounding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/07/19/grounding.html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks back I rearranged my home office and shack. The new arrangement gets my HF station
off of my desk and onto its own shelf, and it’s been sitting there receiving FT8 quite happily while
I’ve been programming and testing a WSJT-X &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/xylo04/wsjtx-go&quot;&gt;UDP receiver&lt;/a&gt; for
Golang. However, today was my first attempt at operating FT8, and unfortunately, something about the
current arrangement is causing my CI-V control to reset every time I transmit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having CAT control reset on transmit is a killer problem for digital modes. With WSJT-X in
particular, the software ends the transmission if CAT resets, so you’ve lost that entire transmit
cycle. I had similar problems in the old desk location with certain bands; for example, I couldn’t
really operate anything below 40 meters due to CI-V resets, and even on 40m I had to limit my power
to keep it reliable. Today’s test on 20m was very discouraging. I used to be able to run 20m at 100W
if I felt the need (usually used less), but today even at QRP, I was having no luck transmitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/7d/HomeEarthRodAustralia1.jpg/548px-HomeEarthRodAustralia1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
A grounding rod (via Wikimedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intuition is that I’m being bitten by the lack of a good station ground. I’ve gotten this far
without needing it, but something about the new configuration is allowing more RF into the shack. I
do have a radial wire on my end-fed long wire antenna, so there’s not a lot more I can do to
optimize the antenna. I’ve been avoiding setting up a station ground because it’s not as simple as
plugging something into a wall socket ground. It requires running a copper strap directly to a
dedicated grounding rod, which among other things requires finding a way to route it through the
exterior wall. I’m on the 2nd floor in the front of the house, so that’s easier said than done.
However, it really is probably the next step in improving the station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, I’m continuing work on writing my own logging software. I’ve decided that I should
pursue creating a hosted web application with offline support. Unique among the web loggers I’ve
seen, I think I can achieve rig control and WSJT-X integration through an
“agent” program sitting on the same computer as the radio interface. The web application can connect
to the agent through a websocket, and the agent will translate between the webapp and
WSJT-X, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hamlib&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;flrig&lt;/code&gt; or whatever else needs to be on the local machine. I have a proof of
concept for the websocket stuff, but there’s still a lot of work to be done on core functionality.
The web app is in Angular with Typescript. While I probably won’t use ADIF as a raw internal format,
I still need to be able to speak it for import and export, and I haven’t found any native Typescript
implementations yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A couple of weeks back I rearranged my home office and shack. The new arrangement gets my HF station off of my desk and onto its own shelf, and it’s been sitting there receiving FT8 quite happily while I’ve been programming and testing a WSJT-X UDP receiver for Golang. However, today was my first attempt at operating FT8, and unfortunately, something about the current arrangement is causing my CI-V control to reset every time I transmit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Field Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/28/field-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field Day" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/28/field-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/28/field-day.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-0a57GdfMqf4/Xv4Li0qjMRI/AAAAAAABv_I/8iI_biF5oucenEeYvudRI3ktqhrzs66PwCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200627_151447.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chris set up at a picnic table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my ham license during last year’s ARRL Field Day, but wasn’t really aware at the time what an
important “holiday” it is to US hams and didn’t participate. This year, I fixed that mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an invitation to join RMHAM at their annual mountain excursion, but family duties kept me
close to home. Instead, I planned to head out to a local park and operate on battery for a few
hours. I don’t really have a great portable kit yet, so I hauled out most of my QTH station. I
replaced my usual mains power supply with a 360 Wh battery, and opted to keep my QTH antenna in
place and instead use a Chameleon portable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Na9nn6lbZkc/Xv4LmMWVfAI/AAAAAAABv_M/n1K38FYDysw1GYVN0nATF2mLy-HqDE8bQCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200627_151939.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;HF station at the picnic table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s gear list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Icom IC-718 (from &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/16/silent-key.html&quot;&gt;Alan’s SK collection&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LDG IT-100 tuner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MFJ 822 power/SWR meter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signalink USB sound card interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2019/11/13/toughbook.html&quot;&gt;Panasonic CF-19 laptop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chameleon MPAS 2.0 with SS-17 vertical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bioenno 30Ah LiFePO4 battery in a Powerwerx MEGAbox&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Powerwerx FSP-110W solar panels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Powerwerx MPPT-150-14.6 charge controller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-IpWizP1sQXM/Xv4Lpf8yj1I/AAAAAAABv_Q/O1OfECFsyJMZDgCnp6mekM4QDlY_z3ZhACLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200627_151456.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Solar panels and antenna&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, most of that gear fit into my trusty ol’ Spec Ops T.H.E. Pack Tactical, minus the battery
and solar panels. It’s not a radio station I’d want to lug up a hill, but crossing the park wasn’t
difficult. Setup went smoothly and I wasn’t missing any critical parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made 32 contacts on 20m FT8 in about 2 hours, and had a teenage kid stop and talk for a few
minutes. Overall, it was an extremely pleasant day to be outside and playing radio.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building A Better Logger</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/20/logger.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building A Better Logger" /><published>2020-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/20/logger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/06/20/logger.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-pWdIhW7iQfg/Xv4EVpx7tFI/AAAAAAABv-s/7jHyGqmPl8oY8WauwiDmx46aTCf_Uc-PgCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/Screenshot%2Bfrom%2B2020-07-02%2B09-58-40.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prototype web logbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been on the air a ton over the past month. I’ve been a little fed up with my logging
software and overall logging strategy. I run mainly Linux on my computers and do a lot of FT8 with
WSJT-X. CQRLog has worked pretty well since it will accept log entries directly from WSJT-X thanks
to UDP integration. However, I’m a programmer and very picky, and there are things in CQRLog that I
just can’t stand. For instance, CQRLog will let you backfill a QSO’s name, city (QTH), state, etc.
from the QRZ.com database for several records at once, but it basically assumes you want to backfill
your entire log; I only want to fill in the last 5 QSOs that are missing that information and then
stop. CQRLog also doesn’t have good merging. It will deduplicate, but it just deletes duplicates
instead of trying to keep relevant information from matching records. That shortfall makes it
painful to run CQRLog on multiple computers, for example a home desktop and a field laptop. To top
it off, CQRLog looks terrible on a HiDPI monitor with scaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I realized my log strategy was flawed. I was uploading my logs from CQRLog to Logbook of the
World and then pulling LotW into my QRZ.com logbook, but eventually realized that LotW was dropping
details like the sent and received RST and TX power. Now I have about 200 records in QRZ that are
missing those fields. CQRLog has the details but can’t help with fixing them; QRZ.com logbook
doesn’t support record merging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-L4lsGQ3hnwo/Xv4EzHXVw8I/AAAAAAABv-0/okuGQc9PKpA_Hpb3xRywNo5kqc6t4_E2gCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/Screenshot%2Bfrom%2B2020-07-02%2B10-01-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Awards map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivated by all of this, I’ve set out to write my own logging software to fit my
personal needs. Right off the bat, I want to have better merging of ADIF files and be able to update
records in my QRZ.com logbook. I also want to introduce interactive Google Maps for awards like
Worked All States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial effort has been a web application in Golang, very similar to Pat since I’ve been doing
some development on that. It’s highlighted some of the difficulty of working with the ADIF format;
I’m really missing my JSON and protobufs. There is a decent Golang ADIF parser written by GitHub
user &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/tzneal/ham-go&quot;&gt;tzneal&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s still a far cry from more modern formats
and generated clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I’ll ultimately keep this web app or rethink it. Sure, I have my award progress map
and I’ll get to the point that I can fix my QRZ.com logs. But if I’m going to invest more time in
this, I don’t really want to make a slightly better CQRLog or a slightly better QRZ.com logbook. The
amateur radio logger space hardly needs another half-baked solution. My goal ought to be bringing
together advantages from many logger applications and being significantly better than what exists
today. But what does that mean, a desktop client that adds peer-to-peer syncing and QRZ.com updates?
A cloud web application with offline capability that can support rig control and WSJT-X integration?
I’m not sure what’s possible yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30 testing</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30 testing" /><published>2020-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/05/30/lora.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-VT6KBUPj5_Q/XtZz37eE6VI/AAAAAAABvlo/hgmsz1SFzzsNDdyJ7rmX0yoavmSU7r-KACK4BGAsYHg/s1600/IMG_20200530_095536.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Custom LoRa remote control relays&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today would have been the day of the annual Golden Gate Dirty 30, had COVID-19 not invaded our
lives. The race didn’t happen, but a couple of us from RMHAM decided to head into Golden Gate Canyon
State Park anyway to test out a new apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the problems we experienced in 2019 was a loss of power at City Lights Ridge, a central point
in the temporary IP-over-microwave network that we set up every year. Rather than haul extra
batteries up the hill, we were looking for a creative way to use power more efficiently, and a
couple of folks came up with a solution. Using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/3079&quot;&gt;Adafruit Feather LoRa 433 MHz modules&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/product/2923&quot;&gt;latching relay FeatherWings&lt;/a&gt;, they built a remote power
control system which would allow them to switch off the network gear when not in use. (I can take no
credit for actually helping with development of the system.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-exCn_dKLGPo/XtZ0SafO3SI/AAAAAAABvl8/-vjqcVza9j8OVMt3GZGhTPq5lM9btoSPACK4BGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200530_095542.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Custom LoRa remote control&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal today was to test propagation and see if they would actually reach where we needed. I hiked
up to City Lights Ridge with a relay module and a remote control; Ben &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KC2VJW&lt;/code&gt; went up Windy Peak
with the same, and Willem &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AC0KQ&lt;/code&gt; started testing with a remote control from near the Tallman
Ranch (which is Aid 1/4 during the race). It took a bit of fiddling with the relay module, but after
resetting it, it did start switching. Willem then hiked down to the Nott Creek Trailhead
(start/finish) and Red Barn. Unfortunately, when I was fiddling with the reset button I apparently
broke the antenna mount solder connections, and by the time Willem made it to start/finish we had a
threatening rain cloud moving in, so we didn’t get a thorough test from Red Barn to City Lights.
However, start/finish to Windy was working well, so that tells us that this LoRa system does have
good propagation even through hilly terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, it was good to get outside and play radio. Most (not all) folks on the trail were
being respectful of social distancing and wearing masks, but the parking lots were quite crowded. I
was glad we got an early start.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>