<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-07T21:18:47+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Alan’s Silent Key Collection</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/16/silent-key.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alan’s Silent Key Collection" /><published>2020-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/16/silent-key</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/16/silent-key.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PBQCrBNjW4k/XlqUbQLXuMI/AAAAAAABt00/B1SKc4F8ycMDeEHLDwa3MMtqvGLUTBbawCKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200210_115422.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Radio equipment on a kitchen table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I had the responsibility of managing a Silent Key collection for the first time. Most hams
will know that SKs are radio amateurs who have passed away. My wife’s uncle Alan passed away in 2017
almost 3 years ago, but I learned over Thanksgiving that he had an amateur license (ex-&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N0JAU&lt;/code&gt;), as
did his father-in-law Dick (ex-&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W7CRZ&lt;/code&gt;) who passed in 2006. Their family still had all of the radio
equipment and didn’t really have a way to distribute it, and were looking to free up the space. I
knew that there are hamfests every couple of months in the Denver area and offered to help sell it
off. Alan’s widow offered that I should keep anything I found useful, which is a very gracious gift,
and send back proceeds from only sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend of Feb. 8th, I drove down to New Mexico where Alan and Dick’s family still lives.
We loaded up several moving boxes of various transceivers, test equipment, and cables. We also took
down a 25’ antenna, which was tricky with no guy system to leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next week, I went about sorting, cleaning, cataloging and pricing the gear. There was
nothing cutting-edge between Dick and Alan’s stuff which was to be expected, but there were a few
gems. Dick had two complete sets of the Kenwood TS-430S including matching tuners, power supplies
and desk mics, as well as several 1960’s Heathkit assembled kits. Dick also had an Icom IC-718 which
I plan to adopt as my first serious HF radio, and not one but two AEA packet modems which should aid
my Winlink experimentation. Alan only held a Tech license and had several VHF mobile radios; I
probably won’t use those for permanent mobile use because I prefer having at least dual-band
capability, but they could be very useful for setting up something like a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tarpn.net/&quot;&gt;TARPN&lt;/a&gt;
node. The collection also included many ham shack staples like dummy loads and RF cable adapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-cygkF-TZU18/XlqTkS49T-I/AAAAAAABt0o/axNvssXSwhUn3xtN830WBFXr4RHe5nr9ACKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200216_083728.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hamfest vendor table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a vendor at a hamfest is very much like being a vendor at the craft sales that my wife and
mother-in-law often do, so they were a lot of help in preparing. On the day of the sale, my
mother-in-law offered to come help me. It was definitely welcome company! We didn’t move much
equipment, but I got feedback that most of my prices were in line with current market values, and
that a lot of it was fondly remembered by those who had used them. I heard a lot of people
especially comment about the Kenwood TS-430S, “That’s a good radio! I got a lot of use out of one of
those!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the sale’s over, I just have to figure out what to do with the rest of it. I don’t plan to
store it all forever, so I’ll need to find homes for the things I’m not keeping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PiPat presentation</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/15/pipat-preso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PiPat presentation" /><published>2020-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/15/pipat-preso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/02/15/pipat-preso.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-wZo-I7wwHps/XkhuUxFSG4I/AAAAAAABtm4/qXtiMbar5gUk0Ze5wxnNHpI8n5E_Tky6ACLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20200118_123819.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raspberry Pi and TNC-Pi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was RMHAM-U Nerdfest, which is “A variety of half hour talks on nerdy topics by participants.”
I gave a presentation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.k0swe.radio/pipat&quot;&gt;PiPat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1D1G5K7JEhATZmsF1oYu3MFntzarn0PokRvu2k5iqmH0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Check out the slides!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visiting California</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/24/visiting-ca.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting California" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/24/visiting-ca</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/24/visiting-ca.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mxcKAYXHSJA/XlrTLWJOCAI/AAAAAAABt1k/TvcIVQd1B40XH-G2aUTUWpDNPvR6WjZpgCKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200123_170739.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View of a Sunnyvale highway&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I had a work trip to the south Bay Area in California, and took an HT to try my hand at
making some local repeater contacts there. I had a couple of nice rag-chews. I learned a lot more
about using the Anytone D878 in VFO mode and with front-panel programming; I get spoiled around home
having the luxury of pre-programming everything with software and transferring code-plugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also took a new ZUMspot hotspot, but didn’t have much opportunity to use it. At the office I had a
great view of the local repeaters from a high floor and didn’t really need the hotspot; at the
hotel, the Wi-Fi had a captive portal and I didn’t have a good way to connect it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JFK Foxhunt</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/15/jfk-foxhunt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JFK Foxhunt" /><published>2020-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/15/jfk-foxhunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/15/jfk-foxhunt.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SVPMs8silVU/XlrVHQjInAI/AAAAAAABt10/Rs9f6YqHrdggSJV1UZ94_pS4wosV7oKYwCKgBGAsYHg/s320/398A5092-84F2-45B7-80B8-6AC936EFCF4A.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Cheyenne Sterner N0CKS and Heather Randall with ARDF foxhunt gear&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I helped a team from RMHAM to introduce some students from JFK High School to amateur radio
ahead of our potential ARISS contact. We did a quick lecture as an overview of amateur radio, then
took the students out for radio direction finding, commonly known in the hobby as foxhunting. The
foxhunt was meant to teach the kids about directional antennas and give them a hands-on activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first experience with foxhunting, and I really enjoyed it. However, I wasn’t very
skilled at guiding my group of students. I’ll have to practice this later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ISS APRS via New Antennas</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/14/iss-aprs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ISS APRS via New Antennas" /><published>2020-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/14/iss-aprs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/14/iss-aprs.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Z2HY3wgP9vo/Xh6bjzIx3fI/AAAAAAABs7Y/3vA7TN5BmVQ2IKU_u-0joMlW2GS18JpawCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/ARISS-APRS%2Bcontact.png&quot; alt=&quot;ARISS APRS website showing K0SWE&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a chance this weekend to install new antennas: an NMO mount for my truck (in addition to the
car I did a few months ago) and a VHF/UHF J-pole in the attic. The NMO install went a little
smoother in the truck than it did in the car, I suppose due to experience, but also because the
larger cab and larger headliner meant I didn’t feel the need to take both B and C pillar trim panels
off, just one side of the truck. The attic antenna went well enough, although my attic has a shorter
peak than I remembered, only about 5 feet. The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrowantennas.com/osj/j-pole.html&quot;&gt;Arrow OSJ 146/440&lt;/a&gt; I bought barely fit. However, it’s
performing really well: hooked up to my new Kenwood TM-D710G, I’m getting APRS packets from up to
110 miles away! I’m not even in that advantageous of a location. (I neglected to check if those were
via digipeater, but regardless, I’m happy!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested out the new D710/attic antenna combo by trying to work the ISS APRS digipeater. It was a
little challenging to figure out the different configuration options for PATH and such, but it was
worth it. I was able to get packets through the ISS digipeater!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
20200114051152 : RS0ISS]CQ,qAR,KC5ILO-12:]ARISS - International Space Station
20200114050936 : &lt;b&gt;K0SWE-9]SYUTVQ,RS0ISS*,WIDE2-1,qAR,W0ARP-15&lt;/b&gt;:`q[El ]/]&quot;E^}Greetings from Denver CO, DM79=
20200114050752 : RS0ISS]CQ,qAR,W0ARP-15:]ARISS - International Space Station
20200114050752 : &lt;b&gt;K0SWE-9]SYUTVQ,RS0ISS*,WIDE2-1,qAR,AD7FC&lt;/b&gt;:`q[El ]/]&quot;E_}Greetings from Denver CO, DM79=
20200114050551 : RS0ISS]CQ,qAR,N6DAN-1:]ARISS - International Space Station
20200114050542 : N6UTC-9]SSURVR,RS0ISS*,qAR,N6DAN-1:`.'pl!bS\]=
20200114050526 : N6UTC-9]SSURVR,RS0ISS*,qAR,N6DAN-1:`.'pl JS\]Resistance is Futile.=
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased as punch! &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AD7FC&lt;/code&gt; is over in Yakima, Washington. There’s definitely room for improvement
on the performance of this system for ISS APRS, maybe with the Arrow hand-held Yagi and actually
tracking instead of relying on raw power and a vertical antenna. But not bad for a first attempt!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Mobile Radio: Kenwood TM-D710G</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/11/kenwood-tmd710.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Mobile Radio: Kenwood TM-D710G" /><published>2020-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/11/kenwood-tmd710</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2020/01/11/kenwood-tmd710.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.kenwood.com/usa/com/amateur/tm-d710ga/images/product_image_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kenwood TM-D710G&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been looking at mobile radios for a while, but the difficult thing about it is that there’s no
radio that does everything. I’ve been looking at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VHF/UHF radios that support digital voice modes like DMR, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VHF/UHF radios that include a TNC and APRS, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all-band radios that do HF in addition to VHF/UHF, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HF-only rigs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing one means giving up on the other modes, or running multiple radios which multiplies cost
and complexity. After much humming and hawing, I decided that packet is one of the things I’d most
like to master (even though the prevalence of packet is supposedly much reduced from its heyday), so
I chose what seems to be the most popular dual-bander with a TNC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kenwood TM-D710G puts out 50W on the 2m and 70cm bands, which is an order of magnitude more
power than the HTs I’ve been using. It has a well-integrated TNC which supports APRS (with built-in
GPS for location), and also more general packet/AX.25 communications, even digipeater operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-GpPA6Dhp-pM/Xhn6l22h8KI/AAAAAAABsys/8q2EN8_EU_Qv5vNAg4-f2tP1C-MLTOEVQCLcBGAsYHQ/s400/crossbandswebfg1.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of cross-band repeating&quot; /&gt;
Cross-band repeating, courtesy Ken Larson KJ6RZ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, it can do cross-band repeating, which is very similar to the SINCGARS retrans I used to
do in the Army. Doing cross-band repeating can allow your vehicle to act as a high-power base
station that can connect back to a permanent repeater on one end, and connect one or more low-power
HTs on the other end, which can be very handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many good YouTube videos for learning different features. I very much appreciated intro
videos from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCo6nMzKerap6RQqS1Va4sTQ&quot;&gt;Jim &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KA6ETE&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lyv56yyi-u4&quot;&gt;couple&lt;/a&gt; of people have videos of working the ISS APRS
digipeater, which would be interesting to try in conjunction with prepping for ARISS. There’s even a
video of someone &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Oo-yigpYj4s&quot;&gt;using DTMF for remote control&lt;/a&gt;;
that’s a bit beyond me at the moment, but it’s nice to know it’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this radio feels a lot more powerful and feature-rich than even my AnyTone AT-D878UV.
I’m excited to explore this and see what it can do!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RMHAM Network Workshop</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/20/microwave-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RMHAM Network Workshop" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/20/microwave-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/20/microwave-workshop.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-pEe11HXT6_0/XfzJsBRbwXI/AAAAAAABsTM/_S3LjM4P4R4pFL9nJ1XciEXzVYZ79MT2gCK4BGAYYCw/s320/IMG_20191214_142621.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Workshop attendees in a conference room&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I was very lucky to get an in-depth look at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/wordpress/amateur-microwave-network/&quot;&gt;RMHAM’s microwave network&lt;/a&gt; by being
invited to a workshop on the subject. It’s an IP-over-microwave network spanning New Mexico to
Wyoming and Pueblo to Grand Junction. It’s an extensive system that carries various amateur radio
traffic; for example, it functions as part of the backbone for the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://colcon.org/wp/&quot;&gt;Colorado Connection&lt;/a&gt; repeater network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complete the workshop I had to dust off a lot of networking knowledge I haven’t exercised in a
long time, particularly OSPF. It’s all fun and games until a rogue static route is breaking routing
everywhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very illuminating class, and hopefully I can start to repay the kindness of the
facilitators, Willem Schreuder &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AC0KQ&lt;/code&gt; and John Maxwell &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W0VG&lt;/code&gt;, by giving back in some fashion. They
have some custom software which manages their configuration and tooling, maybe I can beef that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-why&quot;&gt;But Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t talk much in the workshop about the network’s purpose. Why not have the Colorado
Connection and other clients backed by commercial internet? I guess the answer is that we want to be
independent of the internet to mitigate ISP failures, but that’s increasingly rare. For me there’s a
more foundational reason for the RMHAM network to exist: it keeps ham radio on ham radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard of lots of hams using digital hotspots and the internet to connect to repeaters
worldwide. Hotspots give users access to multiple digital modes and extend the reach of a humble HT
beyond ~30 miles, so they’re great tools. But on some level it feels like cheating. What’s the
difference between using a Zumspot to join a reflector vs using Discord to join a voice chat room,
the fact that you’re going traveling 5 feet over ham frequencies? The advent of the cell phone, and
especially the smartphone, has made the ability to communicate wirelessly to anyone worldwide a
commodity; what makes ham radio still interesting is that &lt;em&gt;we can do it without commercial
infrastructure&lt;/em&gt;. I won’t knock anyone who enjoys using a hotspot as a tool to practice the hobby,
but showing a non-ham a hotspot is not going to convince them to get into the hobby. We need to tout
why ham radio is different from a cell phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what makes systems like the RMHAM network worthwhile. The fact that the Colorado Connection
is independent of commercial infrastructure keeps it “real” ham radio in my mind. The fact that we
get to conceive, install, tinker, keep it running and are not beholden to anyone’s decisions outside
our community, the fact that hams have built it from the ground up, that’s what makes it
special.&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baby steps toward ARISS</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/04/baby-steps-toward-ariss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baby steps toward ARISS" /><published>2019-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/04/baby-steps-toward-ariss</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2019/12/04/baby-steps-toward-ariss.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-4-OrWVSThwQ/Xe22MQ7mlgI/AAAAAAABsEs/MA3n3Xo4QIQaRnoSuGvTmREwkHCk-OlfgCK4BGAYYCw/s320/IMG_20191129_104223.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Arrow antenna and laptop on a car&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I helped Heather Randall from JFKHS and Bob Sterner &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KB0BS&lt;/code&gt; from RMHAM to complete and submit a
proposal to ARISS, so now it’s their hands. It should be 6 to 8 weeks before we hear back. Very
exciting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I tried my hand at receiving an AMSAT signal over the Thanksgiving weekend. Since I
was attempting to receive only, I decided to pipe it through my RTL-SDR rather than an HT in order
to get a visual of the Doppler shift, and had some success. Unfortunately, the particular time I
tried happened to be when no voice birds were overhead, so the only thing I got were what I assume
were telemetry signals, and I didn’t have the decoders installed. At least I got to practice
tracking and adjusting for polarity with the new Arrow antenna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also met with Heather and Bob in person, and we’re planning an ARDF fox hunt with Heather’s
students next week. I get the principles, but this will be my first time actually participating in a
fox hunt. I’m looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AMSAT and ARISS</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/22/amsat-ariss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AMSAT and ARISS" /><published>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/22/amsat-ariss</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/22/amsat-ariss.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/styles/full_width_feature/public/thumbnails/image/44911459904_375bc02163_k.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;International Space Station&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I attended the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/&quot;&gt;RMHAM-U&lt;/a&gt;
lecture series and heard a talk by Doug Tabor &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N6UA&lt;/code&gt; about working amateur satellites, or AMSAT. I
had been exposed to the idea while studying for the exams, but hadn’t really given much serious
thought to actually doing it. The talk was illuminating in terms of operating concepts and concrete
operating procedures. It turns out, there’s a pretty low barrier to entry to get into AMSAT since
it’s low power, line of site, and many satellites use UHF and VHF where even technician licensees
can operate. Something as simple as an HT with a long whip antenna can suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricky parts are pass prediction, antenna tracking and Doppler shift. Pass prediction is made
vastly simpler by smartphone apps, but the satellites don’t always pass directly overhead, so some
orienteering is required. Tracking, i.e. pointing the antenna, can be done by hand, but if you’re
operating by yourself then the antenna always uses up one hand. Then there’s the Doppler shift: the
satellite is operating on a particular frequency (an entire sub-band, actually), but it’s moving
fast enough that one has to tune the receive and transmit frequencies slightly off of the desired
frequency and continuously adjust throughout the pass of the satellite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention that most passes are 15 minutes maximum? An operator has to be extremely efficient and
precise to get contacts. There’s equipment and software to automate all of this, of course, if you
have money to burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk turned out to be timely, because a few days later on the RMHAM mailing list, a call went
out for volunteers to help a local high school (JFK in Denver) with an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ariss.org/&quot;&gt;ARISS&lt;/a&gt; contact proposal. How could I say no helping kids use ham radio to
talk to astronauts in space? ARISS and NASA want to make darn sure that astronauts’ time is not
wasted on technical difficulties, so they have more stringent equipment requirements than your usual
AMSAT operator. However, I’m working with Bob Sterner &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KB0BS&lt;/code&gt; who among many things has
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/expeditions/expedition29/exp29_ham.html&quot;&gt;done a tele-bridge ARISS contact&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qNflnuDlfhM&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;), worked AMSATs and has the proper equipment.
I’ve offered to do as much of the paperwork as I can, and watch and learn the technical side. Even
if we’re selected, the contact wouldn’t be for at least 8 months, but it’s still exciting!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toughbook</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/13/toughbook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toughbook" /><published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/13/toughbook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2019/11/13/toughbook.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-yS9X6eRBrjk/XcyuJF4lNcI/AAAAAAABrms/tfHW6RNVQRMqwQiF-JVEiOBbHAG_hVQVwCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/IMG_20191113_182408.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Panasonic Toughbook CF-19&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s slowly become clear that my penchant for Chromebooks (cheap and simple to manage) will not get
me far in amateur radio. After
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/amateurradio/comments/drmfhh/advice_for_a_hamfriendly_laptop/?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&quot;&gt;asking the internet for recommendations&lt;/a&gt;
and getting a lot great advice, I picked up a Panasonic Toughbook CF-19 MK5. It’s 8 year old
hardware at this point, but:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it sounds like most ham applications don’t require much in the way of CPU or memory,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the IP65 water resistance and general indestructibility is a big plus, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they’re a bargain at ~$300.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that to a brand new “spill-resistant” Lenovo X1 Carbon at $1,500!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve installed Xubuntu 19.10 on it, and the experience was pretty seamless. A couple of notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The touchscreen works, although I can’t figure out how to calibrate it yet. As usual, I’m
&lt;a href=&quot;https://askubuntu.com/q/1188624/129686&quot;&gt;asking the internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The speaker didn’t work directly after install, but after playing around in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alsamixer&lt;/code&gt; and
raising all of the channel levels, I was able to get it working.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The front buttons don’t work out of the box, but apparently there’s a driver running around called
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;panasonic-hbtn.zip&lt;/code&gt;. I’ll have to track that down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mine didn’t come with a GPS module, but eBay has second-hand parts going for $35, so that’ll be a
nice addition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>