<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-08T22:42:50+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">ARES Event: Arapahoe County Fair</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES Event: Arapahoe County Fair" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair.html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 4 days I was assisting &lt;a href=&quot;https://arapahoeares.org/&quot;&gt;Arapahoe County ARES&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arapahoecountyfair.com/&quot;&gt;Arapahoe County Fair&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not sure what I was expecting, but
this event turned out to be very challenging and gratifying!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-x-X4-8FwPxg/YQbOMIZd9GI/AAAAAAAB3jI/dRETzx6zgRYICSTLOe1Xg7Wr6eXqsyNBACPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210723_014648315.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ferris wheel and carnival rides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-aYwCRafAY10/YQbOYqWAJeI/AAAAAAAB3jM/wDEXJDawM7kSN-_5IZItbS2Lw8rYEEO1gCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210724_190545040.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dock Dogs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My role was to walk around the fair as part of a team of 2 or 3 and be extra eyes and ears for the
sheriff’s office and the fair staff. During the course of each day, I ended up averaging about 10
miles walking. We assisted with about 10 lost child incidents where we searched for children or
parents; 3 or 4 medicals where we called the event EMTs out into the fair to help people; and asked
for sheriff support on a couple of unruly customers. Good times!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For the past 4 days I was assisting Arapahoe County ARES with the Arapahoe County Fair. I’m not sure what I was expecting, but this event turned out to be very challenging and gratifying!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES In-Person Meeting</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES In-Person Meeting" /><published>2021-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f.html">&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has of course kept us mostly at home and away from people for over a year now.
But with wide-spread vaccinations, the grip of the pandemic is starting to loosen. Case in point:
last night, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coaresr1d6.org/&quot;&gt;Colorado ARES R1D6&lt;/a&gt; was able to meet in-person for the
first time since February 2020!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NzDnm7_cRA0/YQbL2Bat_kI/AAAAAAAB3i8/U0Np51mejlY0PUVmmXZJNTb7xMTRaj6wACPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210716_014841717.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;R1D6 members training&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-yk4fuMUDVAE/YQbL2NgG1TI/AAAAAAAB3i8/iQX_i7GSQM8VoZD6ppuuAKp3zU0IuFSNACPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210716_011817916.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;R1D6 members training&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on initiating &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrl.org/ares&quot;&gt;ARRL ARES&lt;/a&gt; Task Books. Most members of the unit
have the training to complete Level 1 of the task book without effort, so we worked on some Level 2
skills like front-panel programming a radio, and taking a field report on an ICS-213 with sufficient
detail. It was a lot of fun to see folks in-person again!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The COVID-19 pandemic has of course kept us mostly at home and away from people for over a year now. But with wide-spread vaccinations, the grip of the pandemic is starting to loosen. Case in point: last night, Colorado ARES R1D6 was able to meet in-person for the first time since February 2020!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink Forms in Pat!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/10/pat-forms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink Forms in Pat!" /><published>2021-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/10/pat-forms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/10/pat-forms.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been switching my focus more to the software engineering side of the hobby. I’ve been getting
more and more involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/la5nta/pat&quot;&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt; and have been particularly interested
in the form templates features, which has been available as a beta feature for about a year now. I
can’t take credit for most of the form templates code, most of that was written by Rainer
Grosskopf &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;KI7RMJ&lt;/code&gt;, but I was able to nudge Pat’s founder, Martin Pedersen &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LA5NTA&lt;/code&gt;, into creating a
new release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ZTD3qZ8wOMo/YQbKjeRHGyI/AAAAAAAB3iw/uUqtci1rEZMXNeCk0ygHmYDua-SHhzY_ACLcBGAsYHQ/s320/Screenshot%2Bfrom%2B2021-08-01%2B10-23-11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pat v0.11.0 changelog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, most of the feedback is very positive! There are a couple of bugs to fix and necessary UX
improvements to make, but at least it’s out there in the world!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been switching my focus more to the software engineering side of the hobby. I’ve been getting more and more involved in Pat and have been particularly interested in the form templates features, which has been available as a beta feature for about a year now. I can’t take credit for most of the form templates code, most of that was written by Rainer Grosskopf KI7RMJ, but I was able to nudge Pat’s founder, Martin Pedersen LA5NTA, into creating a new release.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Field Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/26/field-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field Day" /><published>2021-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/26/field-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/26/field-day.html">&lt;p&gt;I was able to get out for a little while today. I worked a little FT-8, and had planned to do some
voice. I started to get a little rain, which I was prepared for. But then the rain picked up and I
had to disassemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/--f3V4oIw0zk/YQbHaCaa6jI/AAAAAAAB3iY/d5_2oSX0sCYXEeyjXQQel58qHA3HUkeogCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210626_200857436.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Field Day station at a picnic table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-HB3R5ej7ftY/YQbIDPn08MI/AAAAAAAB3ig/EWti31CfB8ABLbybqTDEIWcmVtuMje3UQCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210626_193605288.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Field Day station with solar panels&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-f6-veXXdJbE/YQbHaKE3DUI/AAAAAAAB3iY/f4m7LWaYmNkez7x9Ujq4P3QL_1J_Vbe6wCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210626_201125053.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chris at Field Day Station with rain jacket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was able to get out for a little while today. I worked a little FT-8, and had planned to do some voice. I started to get a little rain, which I was prepared for. But then the rain picked up and I had to disassemble.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mountaineer is dead: long live Digirig Mobile</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/23/digirig.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mountaineer is dead: long live Digirig Mobile" /><published>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/23/digirig</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/23/digirig.html">&lt;p&gt;After all that work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/mountaineer&quot;&gt;Mountaineer&lt;/a&gt;, I recently found someone
who was working on a similar project: &lt;a href=&quot;https://digirig.net/product/digirig-mobile/&quot;&gt;Digirig Mobile&lt;/a&gt;
by Denis Grisak &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;K0TX&lt;/code&gt;. It’s pretty much identical in feature set, a quarter of the size, is
similarly &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/softcomplex/digirig&quot;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt; and was designed by an actual
electrical engineer who knows what he is doing. After building cables to interface with the TX-500,
it’s working perfectly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-I99x4_ZeQRg/YQbCTfiwtSI/AAAAAAAB3iA/o6fdzFXPuCIwEyZXXakYqK1AQeYoDEdSgCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210622_154749176.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QRP station with Digirig Mobile in grass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-i8f1P19JXx4/YQbCTXdSOJI/AAAAAAAB3iA/s0vIJPJE_esZnUuDThfRreoziGthznBrwCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210623_153608628.MP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QRP station with Digirig Mobile at a picnic table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke with Denis over email and he gave me some ideas to improve Mountaineer. I’m grateful, but
for now, I think I’m just going to stop development on Mountaineer and guide people towards Digirig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I’m a little relieved. It was a lot of fun developing Mountaineer and building my hardware
skills, but the thought of productionizing it, mass-producing, having to deal with logistics and
payments and customer service… It’s all more than I really wanted to pursue. I’ll leave that to
someone with a more entrepreneurial spirit!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After all that work on Mountaineer, I recently found someone who was working on a similar project: Digirig Mobile by Denis Grisak K0TX. It’s pretty much identical in feature set, a quarter of the size, is similarly open source and was designed by an actual electrical engineer who knows what he is doing. After building cables to interface with the TX-500, it’s working perfectly!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/13/dirty-30.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30" /><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/13/dirty-30</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/13/dirty-30.html">&lt;p&gt;With the pandemic seemingly waning, the Golden Gate Dirty 30 was actually able to happen this year!
Supporting this event two years ago was the first event I supported as a ham operator, and I was
thrilled to get to participate again. This year I was officially part of the RMHAM Tech Team
responsible for setting up and operating the IP-over-microwave network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I volunteered to be stationed up on City Lights Ridge. It’s not a place that the team had stationed
somebody before since it mostly runs itself. However, that site is the linchpin of our operations,
and there had been problems there in the past requiring team members to sprint up the steep trail,
sometimes with heavy additional lead-acid batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-BNArf2gCr8M/YQbFi9oyVPI/AAAAAAAB3iM/t_7pdQCZ5M8r3dUfKj4aY0NAhhkNwSKLgCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210611_193929291._exported_99_1623550275998.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;City Lights Ridge mast with microwave gear&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bIknRQinoCw/YQbFi2uCJSI/AAAAAAAB3iM/V6Q2RNxZkLAbz7xzoPU5nCy9Cdz52SmBwCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210612_122714687.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking from CLR down at Forgotten Valley, Aid 1/4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted to sleep up on top of City Lights Ridge rather than attempt the difficult hike at 04:30 in
the morning. It was a beautiful 36 hours to be up there, and mostly uneventful. At the end of the
event, one of the organizers told me it was a great mental relief having someone up there to assist
if needed. Good times!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With the pandemic seemingly waning, the Golden Gate Dirty 30 was actually able to happen this year! Supporting this event two years ago was the first event I supported as a ham operator, and I was thrilled to get to participate again. This year I was officially part of the RMHAM Tech Team responsible for setting up and operating the IP-over-microwave network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mountaineer actually works!</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/04/mountaineer-works.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mountaineer actually works!" /><published>2021-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/04/mountaineer-works</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/06/04/mountaineer-works.html">&lt;p&gt;I got my latest batch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/mountaineer&quot;&gt;Mountaineer&lt;/a&gt; boards yesterday and
built one of them. It actually works! Woohoo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-VfL97N09OVc/YQbAPWPEZsI/AAAAAAAB3h0/IvbUfpwd2Nk0ADWac1Zud1bCzJsWC8p2ACPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210603_163202077.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QRP station including Mountaineer data interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I got my latest batch of Mountaineer boards yesterday and built one of them. It actually works! Woohoo!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mountaineer works! Sort of</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/05/26/mountaineer-progress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mountaineer works! Sort of" /><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/05/26/mountaineer-progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/05/26/mountaineer-progress.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-vZv1Aw_HLk8/YQarSaAP4iI/AAAAAAAB3hY/nXJIFWxCmPY_74FXMbobaESXGcER9AB8wCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210525_141004702.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;USB hub on breadboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reworking my radio interface board, I eagerly sent it off to JLCPCB for a small batch. I got
them back on May 14th, but for the past two weeks or so they’ve been haunting me. When I plugged
them into the computer, the USB hub would enumerate and show up in the operating system, but the
serial and audio chips would not! It was infuriating! I had to go back to breadboard prototypes to
figure out the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, a component swap I had made was my problem. I had built my separated USB hub prototype
with a TI TPS2044D power management chip, but then decided on the full radio interface I
could get away with the smaller and cheaper TPS2041. Unfortunately, I assumed that I could just
connect it to one of the hub’s overcurrent/enable pairs. After much banging my head against the
table, I’ve found that all the overcurrent pins and enable pins need to be tied together. Rookie
mistake!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bLooF_mi4WY/YQasXtdEHyI/AAAAAAAB3ho/-CYL7KLxbDE8tBEBrNzWitu8cB7bhVxeQCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210525_165745353.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PCB project with ugly soldering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing that with some ugly soldering on the real PCB confirms it. I need a new batch of boards to
fix this properly. But now I know!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On to the real thing</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/22/real-thing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On to the real thing" /><published>2021-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/22/real-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/22/real-thing.html">&lt;p&gt;My work on splitting out individual prototypes of the USB hub, serial adapter and sound card has
paid off! I have working prototypes of all three, and a lot more experience with what support
components are necessary and which are just “nice to have.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-E7E9fFXprVE/YQalRGiukzI/AAAAAAAB3go/B0AArRbzDFkKNHZeEhw1Qp2I37ECriXtwCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/PXL_20210419_025208393.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Separated sound card and serial prototype boards&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-4Nt0GpzIfHs/YQalRb-TAzI/AAAAAAAB3gs/WiE9Oqrm9UUt36tAFzjJ2plPu7TXaSigQCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/PXL_20210419_024006904.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sound card and serial prototypes in use&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this new experience, I’ve started reworking my original design. I also tried out JLCPCB’s
assembly service, and while they probably can’t build the whole thing (don’t have all the parts I
need in stock), they can at least get all the teeny tiny 0603 resistors and capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hHZIIRJNDMw/YQamYqHhYuI/AAAAAAAB3hE/07bZ2Ba1fz8k7Ca-jrt47K1daCE4GRPswCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/PXL_20210421_164931552.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;JLCPCB design and physical board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onward!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My work on splitting out individual prototypes of the USB hub, serial adapter and sound card has paid off! I have working prototypes of all three, and a lot more experience with what support components are necessary and which are just “nice to have.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Interface Thingy Progress, and Dirty 30 Build Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/11/data-interface.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Interface Thingy Progress, and Dirty 30 Build Day" /><published>2021-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/11/data-interface</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/04/11/data-interface.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-Fmywn1iZOWA/YHN5S0tFvvI/AAAAAAAB0Gk/rzj9YY1r-u4tpBkH4xADkCn59bzULUIMgCLcBGAsYHQ/s320/PXL_20210406_191819563.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QFP microchip through a microscope&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been on the air very much over the last month or so. I’ve been focused on continuing with
my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k0swe/tx500-data-interface&quot;&gt;custom radio interface&lt;/a&gt; PCB project. It’s
proceeding well and I gathered a lot of good advice, but I also realized that there are plenty of
unknowns working with new integrated circuits. Do I pull this mode pin high or low? Does the power
input need to be buffered with capacitors or can I get away without that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of all these unknowns, I decided to take one step back and try to create my own evaluation
boards for each of the three major components: a USB hub, a USB sound card, and a USB to serial
converter. That’s essentially what I already have with my consumer devices, but now I’ll try to
build my own versions of these from application notes and validate each of them individually. That
also relieves pressure to get it right the first time in the final form factor that I want; the
evaluation boards are not going to be used in the field, so there’s no need to shrink them to fit in
an enclosure, and I can expose whatever jumpers or test points that I feel are useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had originally set out to do all of this ordering the boards and parts and assembling them myself.
I was able to get some help learning to solder QFP chips which I figured would be the hardest part,
but it turns out that the USB micro-B connectors I chose are even more challenging because they’re
designed for reflow oven soldering, and I’m attempting to use an iron. Given my difficult time
soldering, I’ve also been playing around with a PCB assembly service to assess whether that’s worth
it. I’ll have quite a few prototypes lying around before I arrive at a finished product!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-FzJYmMqkZuc/YHN5FRdHwZI/AAAAAAAB0Gc/63t8I2OtIrsGz6u8jokQiCs0gmT5VIhEwCPcBGAsYHg/s320/PXL_20210411_171611677.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microwave radios deployed in a parking lot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a break from all of that today to join with other members of RMHAM building out the portable
microwave network to support the upcoming Golden Gate Dirty 30 race. It was great seeing folks in
person again! Most of us were at least partially vaccinated against COVID and everyone was cautious
about social distance, and we still got everything put back together. It’s been 2 years since some
of that equipment was used, and there are some additions that the head honchos were eager to add, so
it was definitely worth the time getting it set up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>