<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-26T15:52:41+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box Presentation</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box Presentation" /><published>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-11-winlink-in-a-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winlink in a Box&lt;/strong&gt; is complete, at least as a first iteration. And just in time; I’m going to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1UEEDvDSZwf8X8w8VF07k1LM9I49G5oY94te-oSxsug8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;present&lt;/a&gt;
it tomorrow at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/rocky-mountain-ham-university/&quot;&gt;RMHAM University&lt;/a&gt; Nerdfest.
[Edit: here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/yaV0UdKeh7Y&amp;amp;t=2236s&quot;&gt;video link&lt;/a&gt;!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-12-winlink-in-a-box-inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box inside&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-01-15-ARES-pod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ARES Pod&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncarc.net/&quot;&gt;NCARC&lt;/a&gt; Winter Hamfest up in Loveland, Colorado, and the first
in-person hamfest locally in a good long while. Even with masking and whatnot, it was wonderful to
be back in person to see folks. I spent most of my time at talks. I got a proper introduction to
amateur television from Jim KH6HTV, and that looks like something I’ll have to play with soon! I
also really enjoyed an EmComm talk from Jim AD0ZM, and was particularly interested in the
communications pod he had on display. Sure, I’ve seen pods like it before, but I was reminded that
one of the really nice points about them is that it simplifies setup onsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Jim’s EmComm talk got me back in the thought process of working on Pat integration with VARA.
Pat is sorely lacking VARA support which limits its utility to EmComm folks, and the project has
been languishing. Seeing the pod got me thinking about the reasons I’ve been dragging my feet with
the VARA integration. One of my biggest excuses (for excuse it is) is that setting up both the RMS
station to test against as well as the client station is a lot of toil. It’s not that hard, but it
takes a lot of connecting wires, booting programs and tuning gain levels before I can even start
making any headway. And because I don’t have a lot of space, I inevitably have to take the whole
thing apart within a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my next (hopefully quick) project to springboard me back into Pat+VARA is going to be &lt;strong&gt;Winlink
in a Box&lt;/strong&gt;. I want to take an HT, a soundcard interface and a Raspberry Pi and semi-permanently fix
them in an ammo can. The can should have a power plug on one end, an antenna port on the other, and
it should just work when I power it on. Seal it up so I don’t have to touch the gain knobs, set all
of the software programs to start on boot, and go from zero to working Winlink RMS on VHF VARA FM
within about 60 seconds. All of my work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/pipat&quot;&gt;PiPat&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago will
help, although I’ll no longer be relying on the TNC-Pi. The TNC-Pi only works for AX.25, and for my
purpose I need VARA FM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pat Forms Updates</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pat Forms Updates" /><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/update.png&quot; alt=&quot;Update&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pat officially launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/10/pat-forms.html&quot;&gt;form templates&lt;/a&gt; back in
July, and the reviews since then have been pretty positive! However, there’s definitely room for
improvement, particularly in the process for downloading updated versions of the form templates. To
find out about new versions, Pat has to scrape the Winlink website on a sort of blog post page.
Scraping is notoriously brittle because as soon as someone changes the way the blog page HTML looks,
there’s a high chance of breaking the scraper logic. Sure, we could release a new version of Pat to
fix the problem, but that will require a lot of scrambling on the part of us, the Pat developers,
followed by every user having to download that new version of Pat. What a mess that would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/martinhpedersen&quot;&gt;Martin&lt;/a&gt; (Pat’s founder) had the idea to separate the
scraping logic into an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/la5nta/pat-api&quot;&gt;online service/API&lt;/a&gt; and take the scraper
out of the main Pat code. That way, if the Winlink blog page ever changes, we can change the online
bit. Pat clients that touch our API project don’t have to be aware of the change, and everything
keeps working. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloud WSJT-X</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloud WSJT-X" /><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-11-23-CloudWsjtx.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of CloudWsjtx&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I was approached by Pearce N2LW with an interesting project idea. I don’t
want to spoil the entire idea, but the basic premise is to be able to “play” WSJT-X from anywhere.
With Forester and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kel-agent&lt;/code&gt;, I have a good tech foundation to make that a reality, and Pearce’s
background also lends itself to the project, so we’ve been working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the project needs a basic WSJT-X GUI in a web app so we can see what all WSJT-X’s
UDP interface can and cannot provide, which led to the screenshot above. It’s surprising useful for
making FT-8 QSOs, but there are also some pretty wide gaps in functionality that make it hard to
replicate the full WSJT-X experience. The biggest information gap is the band graph showing the
waterfall of activity. Since that information isn’t available over the UDP interface, we’ll have a
hard time showing the user where they can safely transmit without stepping on another station (or
being stepped on). Still, it gives us a good base to work from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fun with PulseAudio</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fun with PulseAudio" /><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-10-15-digirig-vs-signalink.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of VARA FM in Audacity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken a slight diversion from integrating Pat with VARA because I need a reliable test bed.
Learning BPQ helped with the software side, but I’ve been having enough reliability problems to
start suspecting the hardware. I’ve been trying to use a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://digirig.net/product/digirig-mobile/&quot;&gt;Digirig Mobile&lt;/a&gt; for at least one of the Winlink
stations, either the client or the server, but have consistently had problems trying to use it for
VARA FM. It’s been great for my QRP HF station and FT8/JS8, but for whatever reason, it’s not doing
well with VHF protocols, either AX25 or VARA FM. I really felt compelled to investigate further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some fussing, I found a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://lists.freedesktop.org/archives/pulseaudio-discuss/2021-October/032167.html&quot;&gt;way to set up&lt;/a&gt;
Linux PulseAudio so I could hear exactly what the soundcard interface was sending to the software
modem program, and what the modem was producing. That resulted in the image above. The top window
shows a VARA FM ping exchange with the Digirig Mobile while the bottom shows a SignaLink USB. Within
each window, the top track is the received audio from the radio, and the bottom track is the audio
transmitted out to the radio. The white highlighted portions are the pause between TX and RX.
Notice, the pause on the Digirig is about 2 seconds, where the pause on the SignaLink is about half
a second. The ping response visible on the SignaLink’s RX track is completely in the deaf section of
the Digirig’s RX track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not giving up on the Digirig yet and I’m working with the designer, Denis K0TX, to understand
what’s happening. In the meantime, my VARA FM adventures will need to use the SignaLink.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BPQ for Dummies</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BPQ for Dummies" /><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/BPQ_and_VARA.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of LinBPQ and VARA FM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken the plunge and started learning
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cantab.net/users/john.wiseman/Documents/BPQ32.html&quot;&gt;BPQ&lt;/a&gt; in earnest. It’s a hefty
program, and it’s clear that it has grown organically over many years. Which is to say, it’s
cantankerous to work with, but it does get the job done. I asked one of my Elmers, Willem AC0KQ,
about how to mentally model it, and he basically laughed and told me that it’s fruitless to try and
build a mental model. Just copy other people’s configuration files and modify them to your needs.
Well, so be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willem does have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://prinmath.com/ham/&quot;&gt;script&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bpq-config&lt;/code&gt; that is basically an
installer and setup wizard for LinBPQ. It assumes you’re using a Raspberry Pi and I’m not, but it
did get me a base to work from. Getting a working config means I finally have a working AX.25 and
VARA FM Winlink RMS to test Pat against!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that’s not the end of my problems for testing Pat+VARA. I’ve been using the radio
interface I recently found and love so much, the Digirig Mobile, for one side of my connection.
However, while it worked just fine for me on FT8, I’ve had some issues trying to get it to work for
AX.25 and VARA FM. I think it’s “going deaf” briefly when switching from TX back to RX, just long
enough to miss the reply in AX.25 and VARA FM. Maybe FT8’s turnaround time is just more forgiving? I
need to do more investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Progress on Pat+VARA</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/09/28/pat-vara-progress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Progress on Pat+VARA" /><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/09/28/pat-vara-progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/09/28/pat-vara-progress.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-09-24-vara-fm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two stations running VARA FM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a lot of time developing on &lt;a href=&quot;https://getpat.io/&quot;&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt; this month. For a long time, adding
support for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.winlink.org/tags/vara&quot;&gt;VARA&lt;/a&gt; transport has been a major requested
feature, but it was never prioritized because VARA is only designed for Windows, and Pat’s primary
user base is Linux &amp;amp; Raspberry Pi. However, folks in the community have been experimenting with
running VARA in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.winehq.org/&quot;&gt;Wine&lt;/a&gt;, and have even gone so far as to write an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/WheezyE/Winelink&quot;&gt;installation script&lt;/a&gt;. When someone has made it this easy to
install VARA on Linux, we don’t have any excuses left to delay integrating Pat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been helping to lay some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/n8jja/Pat-Vara&quot;&gt;groundwork&lt;/a&gt; for the modem
driver. At this point I can complete an HF Winlink session, but I need to do a lot more testing
before we hand it over to the general public. I’m battling bad propagation from my QTH (home) HF
station and its poor antenna. There aren’t any VARA FM Winlink gateways within VHF distance, so I’ve
been forced to pursue setting up my own VHF Winlink RMS/gateway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that in turn has forced me to pursue a topic I’ve been avoiding for some time:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cantab.net/users/john.wiseman/Documents/index.html&quot;&gt;BPQ&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an extremely flexible
piece of software that at its heart wants to be a AX.25 packet radio gateway for Winlink and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulletin_board_system&quot;&gt;BBS&lt;/a&gt;’s, but it can be configured for much
more. Because it’s so flexible, it’s also difficult to configure. I took a look at it a couple of
years ago and decided it was too much to bite off at the time, but it’s really the tool I need for
testing Pat+VARA integration, so I’m now climbing the steep learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES Event: Golden Gran Fondo</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/08/31/golden-gran-fondo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES Event: Golden Gran Fondo" /><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/08/31/golden-gran-fondo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/08/31/golden-gran-fondo.html">&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I participated with my own ARES team, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coaresr1d6.org/&quot;&gt;R1D6&lt;/a&gt;, in covering one
of our big annual events, the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.granfondonationalseries.com/gran-fondo-golden&quot;&gt;Golden Gran Fondo&lt;/a&gt; bicycle race. It’s an
arduous event that winds through the mountains near Golden, the longest event being 90 miles long
with about 9,000 feet of elevation gain and loss. Because the mountains have spotty cell phone
coverage, the event staff really appreciate having a team that can keep communications flowing. This
was my first year helping with the event, and I was very glad I did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-08-29-ggf-aid2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GGF Aid 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was stationed at Aid 2 &amp;amp; 4 located at Slough Pond in Golden Gate Canyon State Park. With me there
was a highly respected local ham, Dave &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;WG0N&lt;/code&gt;. It was a mostly uneventful day, only a couple of
minor surprises. Most of the day we spent enjoying the beautiful views of the state park, the buzz
of athletes coming and going, and the chatter of the progress updates over the DMR talk group. All
in all it was a very pleasant day to be out playing radio.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On Sunday I participated with my own ARES team, R1D6, in covering one of our big annual events, the Golden Gran Fondo bicycle race. It’s an arduous event that winds through the mountains near Golden, the longest event being 90 miles long with about 9,000 feet of elevation gain and loss. Because the mountains have spotty cell phone coverage, the event staff really appreciate having a team that can keep communications flowing. This was my first year helping with the event, and I was very glad I did!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES Event: Arapahoe County Fair</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES Event: Arapahoe County Fair" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/26/arapahoe-county-fair.html">&lt;p&gt;For the past 4 days I was assisting &lt;a href=&quot;https://arapahoeares.org/&quot;&gt;Arapahoe County ARES&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arapahoecountyfair.com/&quot;&gt;Arapahoe County Fair&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not sure what I was expecting, but
this event turned out to be very challenging and gratifying!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-07-23-ferris-wheel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ferris wheel and carnival rides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-07-24-dock-dogs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dock Dogs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My role was to walk around the fair as part of a team of 2 or 3 and be extra eyes and ears for the
sheriff’s office and the fair staff. During the course of each day, I ended up averaging about 10
miles walking. We assisted with about 10 lost child incidents where we searched for children or
parents; 3 or 4 medicals where we called the event EMTs out into the fair to help people; and asked
for sheriff support on a couple of unruly customers. Good times!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For the past 4 days I was assisting Arapahoe County ARES with the Arapahoe County Fair. I’m not sure what I was expecting, but this event turned out to be very challenging and gratifying!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ARES In-Person Meeting</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ARES In-Person Meeting" /><published>2021-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/16/ares-f2f.html">&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has of course kept us mostly at home and away from people for over a year now.
But with wide-spread vaccinations, the grip of the pandemic is starting to loosen. Case in point:
last night, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coaresr1d6.org/&quot;&gt;Colorado ARES R1D6&lt;/a&gt; was able to meet in-person for the
first time since February 2020!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-07-16_011817.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;R1D6 members training&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-07-16_014841.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;R1D6 members training&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on initiating &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrl.org/ares&quot;&gt;ARRL ARES&lt;/a&gt; Task Books. Most members of the unit
have the training to complete Level 1 of the task book without effort, so we worked on some Level 2
skills like front-panel programming a radio, and taking a field report on an ICS-213 with sufficient
detail. It was a lot of fun to see folks in-person again!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The COVID-19 pandemic has of course kept us mostly at home and away from people for over a year now. But with wide-spread vaccinations, the grip of the pandemic is starting to loosen. Case in point: last night, Colorado ARES R1D6 was able to meet in-person for the first time since February 2020!</summary></entry></feed>