<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://k0swe.radio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-18T00:49:30+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">K0SWE Blog</title><subtitle>Events and projects for amateur radio operator K0SWE, a.k.a. Chris.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30" /><published>2022-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/06/04/dirty30.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-02-CLR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;City Lights Ridge site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dirty30.org/&quot;&gt;Golden Gate Dirty 30&lt;/a&gt; ultramarathon. It’s always an annual
highlight for Colorado amateur radio emergency organizations because it takes many of our teams
coming together to support this complex event. Hundreds of crazy runners (this year it was
about 300) attempt the 30 mile/50 kilometer course through 7,000 feet/2,100 meters of elevation
climb and descent in a mountainous park with very little cell phone coverage. The ham team’s job is
to make sure every one of them comes down off the mountain before it gets dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain Ham&lt;/a&gt; tech team was on-site early setting up
our IP-over-microwave network. We use the network to connect the 4 aid stations and one mountaintop
checkpoint to the command center at the start/finish line. Each of these sites has RFID readers that
can read the runners’ bibs and check them in as they run past. We also need one more site that the
runners never see: a central point that can see most of the others by line-of-sight which gets set
up on City Lights Ridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second year that City Lights Ridge was my responsibility. About six of us hiked
equipment up to the site and got it all set up and aligned with the other sites. After that, it was
my job to monitor the network and make sure everything stayed running through the race Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-06-02-cping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For monitoring the network, I made use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://prinmath.com/ham/cping.zip&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cping&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; written by
one of my mentors, Willem &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AC0KQ&lt;/code&gt;. It’s a command-line utility that will simply ping a number of
configured IP addresses every so often (default 2 seconds) and display the latency over time as
different colored characters. It’s simple and effective at looking for problems on a medium-size
network like this. Since our network runs almost all MikroTik networking gear, I also made heavy use
of MikroTik WinBox for configuring radios and routers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dirty 30 Build Day</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dirty 30 Build Day" /><published>2022-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/05/15/dirty-30-build.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flyclipart.com/concept-map-diagram-network-icon-network-icon-png-83003&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/concept-map-diagram-network-icon-83003.png&quot; alt=&quot;Network Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the day in Evergreen helping with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dirty30.org/&quot;&gt;Dirty 30&lt;/a&gt; communications dry
run. We set up the comms trailer, all 5 aid stations and checkpoints, and the network center point
at City Lights Ridge. This is a critical day every year to make sure we have everything connected
and ready to deploy the day before the race. A couple of the sites have to be hiked into the
mountains, so making sure all of the gear is present and working is incredibly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I focused on City Lights Ridge since I’m going to be stationed there again during the race. It’s not
the most complex site, but because it’s the network’s central point, it talks to pretty much all of
the other sites. It needs to be set up early and run smoothly. Hopefully the work I did today will
ensure success at the race.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LARCfest</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LARCfest" /><published>2022-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/04/02/larcfest.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fairgrounds.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Boulder County Fairgrounds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it down to &lt;a href=&quot;https://w0eno.org/&quot;&gt;Longmont Amateur Radio Club&lt;/a&gt;’s annual-once-again swapfest. I
took my youngest daughter who had a marvelous time running around, greeting all of the vendors and
looking at all of the bits and bobs. I didn’t find any treasures, but it was great to get some
eyeball QSOs with folks I hadn’t seen in a while. I’m glad these events are finally starting again!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Transmission via Radio</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Transmission via Radio" /><published>2022-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/03/12/data-transmission.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier today I was one of the presenters at another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/&quot;&gt;RMHAM&lt;/a&gt; University
session: Data Transmission via Radio. I joined John W0VG, Willem AC0KQ and Gary WB5PJB in talking
about the Winlink email ecosystem from many different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was given the task of figuring out how to talk about protocols in an understandable way, and I
hope I did the topic justice. I also had a chance to talk about my favorite little Winlink client,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://getpat.io&quot;&gt;Pat&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, anyone who keeps up with my dealings knows that I’m a regular
contributor to Pat, and it was great to sing its virtues to another crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/queen-elizabeth-donald-trump.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Donald Trump standing in front of Queen Elizabeth II&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Videos of all of the sessions have been posted to YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RDUPjlm1LSs&quot;&gt;Gary Sutton WB5PJB - Basic Winlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oiqAAfBgPCo&quot;&gt;Chris Keller K0SWE - Winlink Protocols and Pat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iLtap7mNnyU&quot;&gt;John Maxwell W0VG - RMS Trimode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LCItApXlPPo&quot;&gt;Willem Schreuder AC0KQ - BPQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Earlier today I was one of the presenters at another RMHAM University session: Data Transmission via Radio. I joined John W0VG, Willem AC0KQ and Gary WB5PJB in talking about the Winlink email ecosystem from many different angles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box Presentation</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box Presentation" /><published>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/02/11/winlink-box-preso.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-11-winlink-in-a-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winlink in a Box&lt;/strong&gt; is complete, at least as a first iteration. And just in time; I’m going to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1UEEDvDSZwf8X8w8VF07k1LM9I49G5oY94te-oSxsug8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;present&lt;/a&gt;
it tomorrow at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rmham.org/rocky-mountain-ham-university/&quot;&gt;RMHAM University&lt;/a&gt; Nerdfest.
[Edit: here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fSGivCXoU_0&quot;&gt;video link&lt;/a&gt;!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-02-12-winlink-in-a-box-inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winlink in a Box inside&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winlink in a Box</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winlink in a Box" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2022/01/17/winlink-box.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2022-01-15-ARES-pod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ARES Pod&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ncarc.net/&quot;&gt;NCARC&lt;/a&gt; Winter Hamfest up in Loveland, Colorado, and the first
in-person hamfest locally in a good long while. Even with masking and whatnot, it was wonderful to
be back in person to see folks. I spent most of my time at talks. I got a proper introduction to
amateur television from Jim KH6HTV, and that looks like something I’ll have to play with soon! I
also really enjoyed an EmComm talk from Jim AD0ZM, and was particularly interested in the
communications pod he had on display. Sure, I’ve seen pods like it before, but I was reminded that
one of the really nice points about them is that it simplifies setup onsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Jim’s EmComm talk got me back in the thought process of working on Pat integration with VARA.
Pat is sorely lacking VARA support which limits its utility to EmComm folks, and the project has
been languishing. Seeing the pod got me thinking about the reasons I’ve been dragging my feet with
the VARA integration. One of my biggest excuses (for excuse it is) is that setting up both the RMS
station to test against as well as the client station is a lot of toil. It’s not that hard, but it
takes a lot of connecting wires, booting programs and tuning gain levels before I can even start
making any headway. And because I don’t have a lot of space, I inevitably have to take the whole
thing apart within a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my next (hopefully quick) project to springboard me back into Pat+VARA is going to be &lt;strong&gt;Winlink
in a Box&lt;/strong&gt;. I want to take an HT, a soundcard interface and a Raspberry Pi and semi-permanently fix
them in an ammo can. The can should have a power plug on one end, an antenna port on the other, and
it should just work when I power it on. Seal it up so I don’t have to touch the gain knobs, set all
of the software programs to start on boot, and go from zero to working Winlink RMS on VHF VARA FM
within about 60 seconds. All of my work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/pipat&quot;&gt;PiPat&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago will
help, although I’ll no longer be relying on the TNC-Pi. The TNC-Pi only works for AX.25, and for my
purpose I need VARA FM.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pat Forms Updates</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pat Forms Updates" /><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/12/06/pat-form-updates.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/update.png&quot; alt=&quot;Update&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pat officially launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://k0swe.radio/2021/07/10/pat-forms.html&quot;&gt;form templates&lt;/a&gt; back in
July, and the reviews since then have been pretty positive! However, there’s definitely room for
improvement, particularly in the process for downloading updated versions of the form templates. To
find out about new versions, Pat has to scrape the Winlink website on a sort of blog post page.
Scraping is notoriously brittle because as soon as someone changes the way the blog page HTML looks,
there’s a high chance of breaking the scraper logic. Sure, we could release a new version of Pat to
fix the problem, but that will require a lot of scrambling on the part of us, the Pat developers,
followed by every user having to download that new version of Pat. What a mess that would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/martinhpedersen&quot;&gt;Martin&lt;/a&gt; (Pat’s founder) had the idea to separate the
scraping logic into an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/la5nta/pat-api&quot;&gt;online service/API&lt;/a&gt; and take the scraper
out of the main Pat code. That way, if the Winlink blog page ever changes, we can change the online
bit. Pat clients that touch our API project don’t have to be aware of the change, and everything
keeps working. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloud WSJT-X</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloud WSJT-X" /><published>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/11/23/cloud-wsjtx.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-11-23-CloudWsjtx.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of CloudWsjtx&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I was approached by Pearce N2LW with an interesting project idea. I don’t
want to spoil the entire idea, but the basic premise is to be able to “play” WSJT-X from anywhere.
With Forester and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kel-agent&lt;/code&gt;, I have a good tech foundation to make that a reality, and Pearce’s
background also lends itself to the project, so we’ve been working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the project needs a basic WSJT-X GUI in a web app so we can see what all WSJT-X’s
UDP interface can and cannot provide, which led to the screenshot above. It’s surprising useful for
making FT-8 QSOs, but there are also some pretty wide gaps in functionality that make it hard to
replicate the full WSJT-X experience. The biggest information gap is the band graph showing the
waterfall of activity. Since that information isn’t available over the UDP interface, we’ll have a
hard time showing the user where they can safely transmit without stepping on another station (or
being stepped on). Still, it gives us a good base to work from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fun with PulseAudio</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fun with PulseAudio" /><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/15/pulseaudio.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2021-10-15-digirig-vs-signalink.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of VARA FM in Audacity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken a slight diversion from integrating Pat with VARA because I need a reliable test bed.
Learning BPQ helped with the software side, but I’ve been having enough reliability problems to
start suspecting the hardware. I’ve been trying to use a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://digirig.net/product/digirig-mobile/&quot;&gt;Digirig Mobile&lt;/a&gt; for at least one of the Winlink
stations, either the client or the server, but have consistently had problems trying to use it for
VARA FM. It’s been great for my QRP HF station and FT8/JS8, but for whatever reason, it’s not doing
well with VHF protocols, either AX25 or VARA FM. I really felt compelled to investigate further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some fussing, I found a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://lists.freedesktop.org/archives/pulseaudio-discuss/2021-October/032167.html&quot;&gt;way to set up&lt;/a&gt;
Linux PulseAudio so I could hear exactly what the soundcard interface was sending to the software
modem program, and what the modem was producing. That resulted in the image above. The top window
shows a VARA FM ping exchange with the Digirig Mobile while the bottom shows a SignaLink USB. Within
each window, the top track is the received audio from the radio, and the bottom track is the audio
transmitted out to the radio. The white highlighted portions are the pause between TX and RX.
Notice, the pause on the Digirig is about 2 seconds, where the pause on the SignaLink is about half
a second. The ping response visible on the SignaLink’s RX track is completely in the deaf section of
the Digirig’s RX track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not giving up on the Digirig yet and I’m working with the designer, Denis K0TX, to understand
what’s happening. In the meantime, my VARA FM adventures will need to use the SignaLink.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BPQ for Dummies</title><link href="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BPQ for Dummies" /><published>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://k0swe.radio/2021/10/09/bpq.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/BPQ_and_VARA.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of LinBPQ and VARA FM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken the plunge and started learning
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cantab.net/users/john.wiseman/Documents/BPQ32.html&quot;&gt;BPQ&lt;/a&gt; in earnest. It’s a hefty
program, and it’s clear that it has grown organically over many years. Which is to say, it’s
cantankerous to work with, but it does get the job done. I asked one of my Elmers, Willem AC0KQ,
about how to mentally model it, and he basically laughed and told me that it’s fruitless to try and
build a mental model. Just copy other people’s configuration files and modify them to your needs.
Well, so be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willem does have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://prinmath.com/ham/&quot;&gt;script&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bpq-config&lt;/code&gt; that is basically an
installer and setup wizard for LinBPQ. It assumes you’re using a Raspberry Pi and I’m not, but it
did get me a base to work from. Getting a working config means I finally have a working AX.25 and
VARA FM Winlink RMS to test Pat against!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that’s not the end of my problems for testing Pat+VARA. I’ve been using the radio
interface I recently found and love so much, the Digirig Mobile, for one side of my connection.
However, while it worked just fine for me on FT8, I’ve had some issues trying to get it to work for
AX.25 and VARA FM. I think it’s “going deaf” briefly when switching from TX back to RX, just long
enough to miss the reply in AX.25 and VARA FM. Maybe FT8’s turnaround time is just more forgiving? I
need to do more investigation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>